<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Goodnes; the blessed mans badge: or Gods character stampt on mans conscience In two sermons before the most excellent Prince Charles. By Richard Myddleton his Highnesse chaplayne.</title>
            <author>Middleton, Richard, d. 1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17871</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107387</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843088</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843088</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7797</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07488)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7797)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 584:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Goodnes; the blessed mans badge: or Gods character stampt on mans conscience In two sermons before the most excellent Prince Charles. By Richard Myddleton his Highnesse chaplayne.</title>
                  <author>Middleton, Richard, d. 1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 166, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Goodnesse.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7797:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOODNES; <hi>The bleſſed mans Badge: OR</hi> Gods Character ſtampt on mans Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In two Sermons before the moſt excellent Prince</hi> Charles.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Myddleton</hi> his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Chaplayne.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 145.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord is good to all, and his mercies are ouer all his workes.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>It is the ſumme of all Religion, to imitate him thou doeſt worſhippe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes,</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7797:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7797:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE NOBLE and Vertuous Lady, <hi>the Lady</hi> Olyffe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pylton, <hi>the continuance</hi> of all graces here, and <hi>the fruition of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall</hi> happines <hi>in Heauen.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right worthy Lady:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Iue mee leaue, I beſeech you, to preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Worth with this lowe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſement of my loue. Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, I confeſſe, is the value of paper preſents, and of ſo much the leſſe account, by
<pb facs="tcp:7797:3"/>how much our age hath made the number of bookes to bee the medicine or purgation of idle or diſtempered braines; and medicine, I wiſh that truely I might haue ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it.</p>
            <p>But bookes, which ſhould be as Apothecaries ſhoppes, and wiſe Phiſitions ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, furniſhed with all manner of remedies for ſick and diſeaſed Soules, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, banes to the Soules and peſts to the bodies of the readers, whilſt the ſubiects handled in them, are fitter to be ſuppreſſed then printed.</p>
            <p>Mine, I dare not commend to be ſuch as it ſhould be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is maine: but thus much I preſume to warrant, that had the worthineſſe of the matter beene ſo happy
<pb facs="tcp:7797:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>to light in a hand, skillfull to diſcipher the true price and pretious value of that good man which is the ground of my diſcourſe, I might right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue ſaid of it, as the good king ſpake of <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſword,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 21.9.</note> there is none to that, giue it me.</p>
            <p>The leaſt birds haue euer the ſweeteſt voyces, and this ſmall grayne of goodneſſe, which is the <hi>All</hi> of man, thus hammered out into all the fayre wreaths of golden gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to adorne the Soule, will (I doubt not) finde accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with all ſorts, who are not altogether auerſe from goodneſſe, louing the fooliſh new fangled dreſſings of the vaine world better, then the graue &amp; rich ornaments of a ſanctified Soule.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7797:4"/>
To your Ladiſhippe is this labour due from mee, who haue been long acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with as great a meaſure of goodneſſe in you, as I ſhall euer hope againe to finde in any. Your godly patience in great, and greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, your ſweete and diſcreete deportments, your vertuous diſpoſition to all goodneſſe, your labour to performe that which is the Soule of all Religion, euen goodneſſe, which is all that is deſired of a man, hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged mee to dedicate this good Man, or man of goodneſſe, to your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as not thinking it fit to diuorce thoſe ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ioyned together.</p>
            <p>Wherein forgiue mee Madam, I pray, this error
<pb facs="tcp:7797:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>in ioyning a dead and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary man to a liuing and a gracious Lady, which I could not auoide, being diſappointed of ſuch a liuing man for ſuch a Woman. Yet doubt I not, ſuch is your noble diſpoſition, but that which once had the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious eare of a moſt Godly, and excellent Prince to entertaine it, ſhall gaine the noble and louing hand and heart of a vertuous Lady, to well-come it; and then haue I my deſire, though the tooth of enuy bite neuer ſo deepe.</p>
            <p>Howſoeuer it fall out, this I haue aduentured on for the common good, but chiefely for the freeing of my ſelfe in part from the juſt imputation of vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:7797:5"/>who owing ſo much reſpect to your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhippe, muſt craue to haue this little peece of Coyne laide vppe in your Cloſet, as an acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a greater debt. In the meane time, I ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer pray, that your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe may haue the hope of the Saints who liue, and the happines of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſeaſed who reſt from their labours; which with all Earthly bleſſings conducing thereunto, our good God for his mercies ſake in Chriſt aſſure and multiplie vpon you, and yours to the full, a vpon him who will euer be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Ladyſhippes true friend to command,</hi> Richard Myddleton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7797:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>GOODNES, The bleſſed mans Badge.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PRO. 29.22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>That, that is to be deſired of a man is his goodneſſe, <hi>or</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of a man is his kindneſſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S there are various and diuerſe ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings of theſe wordes, ſo there are diuerſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions ariſing from them. For firſt, ſome reade them thus,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> There is nothing that a man (chiefly a rich man) ſhould ſo much deſire,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> .2</note> as to doe good from the heart: and what can be gathered hence, but that rich &amp; great men ought
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7797:6"/>to be good men aboue all others? Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſome thus: <hi>Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia hominis, miſericordia eius;</hi> Gods mercy is mans deſire; refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Pronoune, his, vnto God, of whom <hi>Salomom</hi> had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before: man deſiring no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world ſo much, as to haue God to be mercifull to him: and what can be gathered hence, but that it is the Lords mercy we are not conſumed?<note place="margin">Lam. 3.22</note> Thirdly, ſome thus:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Deſiderium hominis eſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordia eius;</hi> The deſire of man is to haue mercy on others: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the Pronoune, his, vnto man. For man ought aboue all things to delight in mercy to man;<note place="margin">Mat. 9.13</note> ſeeing our Sauiour ſaith, I will haue mercy, not ſacrifice; &amp; commands man to bee mercifull,<note place="margin">Luk. 6, 36</note> as our heauenly Father is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And very iuſt it is, that thoſe who haue receiued much mercy, ſhew much vnto others: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing an hundred thouſand talents forgiuen them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 8, 24</note> ſhould forgiue an hundred pence to others. And
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7797:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>what can be gathered hence, but that there is no good in him that is not mercifull? Fourthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> others do giue this ſence of them; that many men deſire to ſeeme merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and good: and what can be gathered hence, but that there are more hypocrites then good men in the world? Laſtly, Saint <hi>Ierom</hi> and others collect this ſence; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that the poore man is mercifull, and compaſſionate towardes others, out of the experience of his owne wants, according to that of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, Non ignara mali, miſeris ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currere diſco,</hi> My owne wounds haue taught mee to conſider o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers woes. And what can be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered hence, but that there is moſt true goodneſſe, where are leaſt goods? But the beſt ſence is, that goodneſſe, that is to ſay, to liue holily and godly, and to doe good to others, is the whole duty of man:<note place="margin">Eccl. 12</note> as the wiſe Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher hath well expreſt it, Feare God and keepe his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: for this is the whole du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7797:7"/>of man.</p>
            <p>Albeit I may ſeeme at the firſt bluſh, to haue layd my founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a barren ſoyle, ſince good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath ſo little ground in this world; yet I will labour to bring timber and materialls out of my Text, to make the building, though not very beautifull, yet (I am ſure) very profitable, which is the ſcope of my proiect in this little frame.</p>
            <p>The ſtructure of which little building ſtands vpon foure co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnes or pillars.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, goodneſſe.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is the generality of the requiſition of it at our hands; for no man is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from this duety; in that he ſaith, indefinitly of a man, not this or that man, reſpectiuely. The third is the perſons deſiring this duty at our hands:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that, that is to bee deſired; not that, that this man, or that deſires, not that our friends onely doe deſire; but that, that is to bee deſired: that is, that, that all the things of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7797:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>worlde deſires of a man, is his goodneſſe. For firſt, all that our good God for all his goodneſſe to vs deſires at our hands, is but goodneſſe. Secondly, all that the Angels deſire of vs, is but good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Thirdly, what all men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of vs, is but goodnes. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what our ſelues deſire of our ſelues, is but goodneſſe. Fiftly, what all the creatures of the world doe deſire of vs, is but goodneſſe. The fourth pillar, is the reaſon, enforcing this moſt excellent dutie of goodnes. And in the Text, I finde ſixe veines of perſwaſion full of pregnant rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to enforce it. The 1. is, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitas officij,</hi> The facility of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: in that it is but one duty, in which all other duties are perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. The 2. is, <hi>Necesſitas officiij,</hi> The neceſſity of the dutie: the bond and obligation whereby we are tied to doe this duty vnto all: namely, to God, to the holy Angels, to all men, to our ſelues, and to the creatures; to all which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7797:8"/>we are by many and many obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations bound, but vnto God in an infinite obligation: in that he ſaith, that, that is to bee deſired of a man. The 3. is, <hi>Modus offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij,</hi> The manner of the ſeeking of this dutie at our hands: it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, beſought, intreated, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, by all ſweet meanes ſought for: whereas, it might haue been commanded. The 4. is, <hi>Tempus officij,</hi> The time when this duety is to bee performed. It is euen now to be deſired, whileſt wee liue heere, whileſt wee are in health, whileſt the voyce of the Turtle is heard in our Land, whileſt we enioy theſe many and vnſpeakeable bleſſings of peace, plenty, &amp; the running ouer of our cup. The 5. is, <hi>Familiaritas offieij,</hi> The familiarity and naturalneſſe of the duty, ſeeing goodneſſe is ſuch, as that no creature, (much more man) but hath a particular goodnes in it ſelfe. Laſtly, <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia officij,</hi> The dignity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the duty: in that hee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7797:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſayd, <hi>quod,</hi> that, euen that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent duty of goodneſſe, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but that, not power, honour, riches, wiſedome, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the like, but good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>If I might be ſo happy to lead your worthy and prudent eyes to beholde all the roomes of this little frame at this time, I ſhould reioyce: if not, I will leaue the reſt to caſt your gracious eyes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, when you pleaſe to come this way next.</p>
            <p>The firſt columne or pillar is the duty it ſelfe, <hi>Bonitas,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Where I beſeech you giue me leaue to vſe theſe few quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rees. 1. What this goodneſſe is.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 2.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Why goodnes is deſired at our hands before greatneſſe, power, honour, riches, vnderſtanding, wiſedome, knowledge, and the like excellent things: or rather, why this &amp; not any of them at all elſe, which yet are ſo much deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſought for by vs. 3.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> How can goodneſſe be ſo deſired of all,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7797:9"/>and practiſed of ſo few. To which I wil adde a fourth quaere, <hi>An ſit bonitas,</hi> Whether there bee any ſuch thing as goodneſſe, and where it is to be found.</p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>quid,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> what is this goodneſſe. And well may we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what it is, that is ſo great, and yet ſo little. So great, that it includes all our duties to God, to man, to the creatures; and yet ſo little, that it cannot bee found amongſt any of our duties: ſo great, that it cannot enter in at the gates of our Cities, Townes, Houſes, or Churches: ſo little, that it cannot be found in any of them. That deuout and good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeaking of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,<note place="margin">Ber.</note> ſaith, that it is <hi>Maximum in minimo,</hi> The greateſt thing that can be, in the leaſt roome that can be. For in the heart of a good man, which is a very little thing, is found a good conſcience, which is the greateſt thing in the world. And herein, it is contrarie to the euent of them that digge for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7797:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>mynes of golde and ſiluer, for they finde <hi>Minimum in maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> a little gold or ſiluer in a great lumpe and maſſe of lead, or other met tall. But in the hart of a good man, that is ſo little, it will not giue a Kite his breake-faſt, is <hi>Maximum in minimo,</hi> The greateſt thing that can bee, in the leaſt roome that can be; that is, a good conſcience, goodnes it ſelfe, that delights both God and man. Therefore no maruell ſeeing goodneſſe ſo great, if it hardly get into ſo narrow a roome as mans heart.</p>
            <p>But I muſt tell you what this goodneſſe is. Wee may ſay of goodneſſe, as the learned ſay of God: that hee onely can bee knowne <hi>Per viam remotionis:</hi> namely, that he is not the heauen, nor the earth, nor the Angels, nor the ſpirits, nor any thing that we ſee: ſo goodneſſe it is not Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and power, it is not riches and pleaſure, it is not birth or beauty, it is not prudence &amp; knowledge,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7797:10"/>nor is it any thing whereof wee haue moſt plenty, though it bee more worth then all theſe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: But wee may ſay of it truely,<note place="margin">Gen. 19, 20</note> as <hi>Lot</hi> ſayd of <hi>Zoar,</hi> Is it it not a little one, and my ſoule ſhall liue? I will then aduenture to ſay, that goodneſſe is a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, whereby we communicate to others, all the good things that are in vs, or belong vnto vs, for their good. This definition, I grant, is too narrowe for good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for it deſerues a larger roome then definitions afforde: yet if I ſhould inlarge it neuer ſo much, I ſhould ſcarcely get any one within the ring of it.</p>
            <p>Now this goodneſſe doth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect the body, or the minde. Goodnes concerning the minde or ſoule of man, is to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, partly by counſell, partly by example of life, to gaine the ſoule of our brother to god: and to this goodneſſe, are theſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons required. 1. To admoniſh the vnruly. 2. To comfort the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7797:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſtreſſed. 3. To beare with them that are weake. 4. To be patient towards all men. Of theſe foure Saint <hi>Paule</hi> hath giuen vs theſe precepts. 5.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5, 14</note> To chaſtice the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate. 6. To pray for all men of what condition ſoeuer. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that olde verſe; <hi>Conſule, caſtiga, ſolare, remitte, fer, ora.</hi> Goodneſſe reſpecting the body, conſiſts in many actions. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thoſe foure which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our commands, to feed the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry,<note place="margin">Mat. 25, 35, 36 2. Sam. 2 Deut. 15; 7, 8.</note> cloath the naked, lodge the ſtranger, viſite thoſe ſicke and in priſon. 5. To bury the dead. 6. To lend liberally and freely to the decayed and impriſoned. All ſix duties included in this verſe: <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſito, poto, cibo, redimo, tego, colligo, condo.</hi> So then wee ſee what this goodneſſe is, and in what &amp; how many actions it ſtands. Firſt then, if you aske mee wherein we muſt ſhew this goodneſſe: I anſwere, in all the gifts and graces of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and minde,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3</note> in our temporall goods and liues alſo, if neede ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7797:11"/>require. Secondly, if you aske me, why wee muſt ſhew this goodneſſe. I anſwere: becauſe we are all members of one body; and ſtand in neede of mutuall helpe and comforts,<note place="margin">Ph. 4</note> without which, neyther the body, nor members could continue in any perfect health.</p>
            <p>But I may goe a degree or two higher, and doe no iniury vnto goodneſſe. And then I may ſay, that it is fully conteyned and expreſſed in theſe two words: <hi>Pietas, &amp; Probitas,</hi> piety and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty. That, is exerciſed in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine things: this, in humane. Theſe are the two golden pillars of all goodneſſe. Theſe are the two gliſtering torches, that doe light vs to eternall happineſſe. Wouldeſt thou haue the great God propitious vnto thee? <hi>Viue piè,</hi> liue a godly life. Wouldeſt thou haue man beneuolent and louing vnto thee? <hi>Viue probè,</hi> liue honeſtly. Wouldeſt thou make them both thy friends?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7797:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>ioyne them together in thy whole life, ſo ſhalt thou with one labour binde both God and man vnto thee: the one of theſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other will not ſerue thy turne. Piety without Probity and honeſty is nothing worth; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity and honeſty without piety and godlineſſe, is leſſe worth. Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety without probity is ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: probity without piety ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, the one without the other, is altogether ruinous: but ioyne them both together in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wedlocke, and thou ſhalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer make aberration from the chiefeſt good.<note place="margin">Hierocles</note> For the heathen man ſpake truely, <hi>Finis virtutum charitas, principium<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pietaes:</hi> The end of vertues, is charity, and the beginning is piety. And to the ſame purpoſe another as well: <hi>Nulla eſt via alia quâ ad felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem eatur, quàm pietas.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iamblicus</note> There is no other way to felicity, then pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety. The diuine truths appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſame,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> that godlineſſe is profitable to all things, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7797:12"/>hath the promiſe of the life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8</note> and of that that is to come.</p>
            <p>What made <hi>Socrates</hi> to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed the beſt and moſt happy man of his time? Was it not this onely, that hee conſecrated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the loue of piety, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity, godlineſſe and honeſty? <hi>Zenophen</hi> reports this of him: <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat adeo religioſus, vt ſine Dei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio nihil ageret; adeo iuſtus, vt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ne exigua quidem in re noceret, prodeſſet autem ijs maxime, qui ipſo vterentur; adeo continens, vt nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> id quod incundius er at, meliori ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poneret.</hi> He was ſo religious that he neuer did any thing without the counſaile of God; ſo iuſt, that he neuer hurt any man, no not in the leaſt thing, but helped them exceedingly, who would vſe his meanes; ſo continent that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer preferred that which was more pleaſant, to that which was much better. Behold an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable patterne of goodneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what and how great ſtudy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7797:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>and care this heathen man pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the practiſe of theſe two worthy parts of goodneſſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what infamy this Gentile caſts vpon vs Chriſtians; nay what iuſt condemnation. Thus muſt we doe, if euer we will doe the duety of my text; if euer wee will be good men, if euer we will come in the preſence of God.<note place="margin">Plato</note> For ſo could the diuine Philoſopher aduiſe: Let this, ſaith he, be thy onely ayme, <hi>Dei cultu &amp; vitae pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate,</hi> by the worſhippe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, and purity and cleanneſſe of life, to obtayne a wiſhed and happy end at the laſt. Now this piety, that you may the better know wherein it conſiſts, doth exerciſe it ſelfe eyther in the outward worſhippe of God, or in the outward and inward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe of God, together. The inward worſhippe of God alone, and by it ſelfe; which conſiſts onely in the minde and inward man, is practiſed in theſe two du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; the firſt, is the knowledge
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7797:13"/>of God, the ſecond, is the feare of God: by theſe two, as by two fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer conduits, doe piety and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion flow into the affections and minds of men.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the knowledge of God,<note place="margin">Io. 17.3.</note> our Sauiour witneſſeth, This is life eternall to know thee to be the onely very God, and whom thou haſt ſent, Ieſus Chriſt the ſame doth the Apoſtle:<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14</note> How ſhall they call on him, in whom they haue not beleeued? And how ſhall they beleeue in him, of whom they haue not heard? This truth is ſo pregnant, that the very heathens haue acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged it: one of them ſaying, <hi>Deum colit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen.</note> 
               <hi>qui nouit,</hi> Hee doth worſhippe and feare God, that knowes God. And another of them:<note place="margin">Iambl.</note> 
               <hi>Dei cognitio ſimilem Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis reddit,</hi> The knowledg of God, makes a man like vnto the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
            <p>Secondly for the feare of God, is it not the beginning of al wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12 13.</note> Feare God and keepe his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7797:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>commandements, for that is <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum hominis,</hi> All the whole duty of man: this was alſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged euen by the heathen wiſe men. One of them could ſay, <hi>Quis non timet omnia prouidentem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic.</note> 
               <hi>cogitantem, &amp; animaduertentem?</hi> Who is it, that doth not feare the all-prouident, all-ſeeing and all-puniſhing God? The glory of this dutie, did the heathen king <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſee, ſo much innobled in <hi>Zenophons</hi> Hiſtory: who dying, called his two Sonnes vnto him, and left them this golden Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; <hi>Pertimeſcite Deos, O Filij, vt nihil impij, nihil nefarij vel commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, vel deliberetis.</hi> O my Sonnes, I beſeech you feare the Gods, that you neuer eyther commit, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate vpon, any impious, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farious or vngodly thing. O how wiſe was this Father (if hee had knowne the true God) to leaue to his poſterity ſuch an ineſtimable pearle by teſtament? And how happy thoſe Sonnes, to whom ſuch an inheritance, more rich
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7797:14"/>then all the Patrimonies of the world, was demiſed and giuen? to whom <hi>Timor Dei;</hi> the feare of God was left as Legacy, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of which, all other vertues, are but as <hi>Strepitus verborum,</hi> the ſound of words without matter. I will adde to this a Legacy of the ſame nature, but better dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, I thinke in the world not ſuch another to paralell it: that of good king <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Salomon</hi> his Sonne:<note place="margin">1. Chron. 28.9</note> And thou <hi>Salomon</hi> my Sonne know thou the God of thy Fathers, and ſerue him with a perfect heart, and with a willing minde: for the Lord ſearcheth all hearts, and vnderſtandeth all the imaginations of thoughts: If thou ſeeke him, he will be found of thee; but if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off for euer.</p>
            <p>How many ſhall wee finde in our times, who will take it in great dudgeon and deriſion, if you tel them, that they haue none of this goodneſſe in them, no knowledge of God, no feare of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7797:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>God? And yet their whole liues ſhewes them to haue no more of eyther indeede then <hi>Cyclops</hi> had,<note place="margin">Eurip.</note> whoſe goodneſſe in the Poet, is thus depainted, <hi>Non vlla numina expaneſco Coelitum, ſed victimas ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni deorum maximo ventri offero: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os ignoro caeteros.</hi> I feare no powers of Heauen, ſaith <hi>Cyclops,</hi> but I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Sacrifices to one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of the Gods, my belly, other Gods I know none. Such are they that conſecrate more dayes and yeeres to their pleaſures and luſts, then houres or minutes to the knowledge of God; ſuch as that wicked iudge, that neyther feare God, nor reuerence man;<note place="margin">Luc. 18</note> ſuch as dedicate moſt of their golden time, to paint and varniſh an vgly face, to deck and dreſſe a rotten, filthy, ſtinking car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſe.</p>
            <p>The internall, and externall worke and ſeruice of God toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being the ſecond part of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and conſiſting both in the inward affections of the heart, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7797:15"/>outward geſtures and actions of the body, I reduce to theſe two duties. The firſt is prayer, vnto God; the ſecond is, prayſe and thankeſgiuing vnto him, for his benefits. For as God is a moſt pure eſſence, ſo will he be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped and ſerued with a pure and vncorrupt minde and voice. The firſt of theſe duties is prayer, which is ſo powerfull with God, if it be put vp with a liuely faith, a holy zeale, and a penitent heart, that as a learned Father ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit inuincibilem,</hi> it ouercomes the moſt inuincible God; and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable a meſſenger withall,<note place="margin">Io. 16.23.</note> as that whatſoeuer we aske in faith, we ſhall obtaine. This opens the gates of Heauen at his pleaſure, and ſhuts them: This ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour preuailes, in what meſſage ſoeuer it be ſent.<note place="margin">Iac. 5.15.</note> The Oracle of <hi>Inpiter Hammon</hi> being conſulted by the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Athons,</hi> why the Gods vntill that time bad giuen victory to the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians,</hi> and not to them, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7797:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>That the cauſe was, for that the prayers of the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> were to them more pleaſing, then all the Sacrifices of the <hi>Graecians:</hi> ſhewing what acceptance prayer had with God.<note place="margin">Epictetus</note> Whence the wiſe and learned heathen was wont to ſay, that if wee did rightly inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate God, it would come to paſſe, that by his Angels he would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh vs of the chiefeſt and beſt things.</p>
            <p>Moſt high and wonderfull pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges are theſe: but how may I a ſilly worme, vnworthy to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the preſence of his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and goodneſſe, frame my pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition and ſuite to the great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty of God? I will tell thee. Learne of that moſt heauenly Teacher ſaying vnto thee: when thou prayeſt, ſay,<note place="margin">Luc. 11.1</note> Our Father which art in Heauen. But if thou wilt not heare God himſelfe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thee to pray, learne of that heathen, firſt to deſire of God that he would graunt vnto thee,<note place="margin">Zenophon</note> 
               <hi>Vt ſentias, loquaris, agas, quae ipſi
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7797:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>gratiſsima ſunt:</hi> That thou mayeſt vnderſtand, ſpeake and doe the things that are to him moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and to thy friends and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth moſt glorious and profitable.</p>
            <p>The ſecond duty of the ſecond part of piety is prayſe and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing vnto God for his benefits. Of which I remember what <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> the <hi>Iewe</hi> writ: That a certaine Prophet being demanded of God if hee deſired any thing in this moſt beautifull frame of the World, to the further perfection thereof, anſwered; that all things were moſt full, perfect and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, yet one thing hee required more, <hi>Laudatorem horum ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem:</hi> A voice to ſet forth the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of theſe things; which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere ſo much pleaſed the Father of this vniuerſe, that not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there was heard a moſt muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſound and Harmony from that only virgin of all diuine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, Memory.</p>
            <p>This is a principall part of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7797:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>worke and ſeruice that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of vs, namely, that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and make knowne to the World, how great his power, wiſedome, and goodneſſe is. And who are theſe muſitions, theſe ſweete ſingers, that make ſuch heauenly harmony in the eares of the Almighty, but we mortall men, of whom he requires this worſhippe, this ſeruice, this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? And what is this for ſo many benefites, for ſo great goodneſſe to vs? Why are we ſo ſlow and negligent in this duty, wherein the very birds of the ayre are ſo diligent? <hi>Si luſcinia eſſem,</hi> ſaith the learned heathen,<note place="margin">Epictetus.</note> 
               <hi>Facerem quod luſcinia; cum autem homo rationalis ſim, quid faciam? Laudabo Deum, nec ceſſabo vnqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vos verò, vt idem faciatis, hortor.</hi> If I were a Nightingale, I would do as the Nightingale doth; but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I am a reaſonable man, what ſhall I doe? I will prayſe and magnify my God, nor will I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe to do it; and my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7797:17"/>is, that you ſhould alſo doe the ſame. For as <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſayd well, hee doth moſt eaſily obtaine his ſuite at Gods hands, not who in aduerſity flattereth him, but who in a proſperous eſtate remembers him. Yet all theſe excellent du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of goodnes and piety, as the knowledge, feare, prayer, and praiſe of God, are but <hi>cadauera,</hi> dead bodies, (and ſo they were in the hearts of all the Heathen, whom God did not further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten) except they be animated by a liuely faith, and tempered with the liuely heate of the loue of God. But when theſe two do make way for the worſhippe and ſeruice of God, and duties of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then is our knowledge, feare, prayer, and praiſe, full of life, then is our ſeruice acceptable vnto him, and not elſe.</p>
            <p>What then ought Kings and mighty men of the earth to doe in this duty of prayſe, but with king <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> if any proſperous thing befall them, not to growe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7797:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>proud, and contemne any man in reſpect of themſelues, but to giue thankes vnto God, in whoſe hands are not onely the hearts of Kings, but euen all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs vnto them? What ſhould the wiſe men of the world doe, but with <hi>Socrates,</hi> ſacrifice vnto God, euen for the fruits of the earth? What ſhould all men do, Kings, and Councell, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, but with <hi>Cicero</hi> and the <hi>Romaines,</hi> ſupplicate our good God, and praiſe his bleſſed name, for that hee hath deliuered, <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem incendies, ciues caede, Italiam bello,</hi> The City from burning, the citizens from ſlaughter, and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly</hi> from warres, when <hi>Catiline</hi> was vanquiſhed? Thus ſhould wee bee affected in euery deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, yea in euery bleſſing: not to think it is our owne wiſedom or prouidence, our owne bow &amp; ſword, our owne worth and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that procures theſe good things vnto vs, and preſerues vs from ſo many iudgements: but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7797:18"/>the onely goodneſſe of God, and that to prouoke vs vnto this duty of goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond pillar of goodnes is probity and honeſty of life; which is as the lampe and light by which wee ſhew our piety &amp; goodneſſe to the view of the world. This is that grace, by which in the things of this life, wee behaue our ſelues aright, as becommeth the children of God: and this is of two ſorts. For firſt, it either reſpects our ſelues, and ſo theſe vertues belong vnto it: fortitude, temperance, magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, patience, continencie, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, chaſtity, parſimony. Wherin I pray you obſerue, what is written of <hi>Pomponius Atticus,</hi> one of the richeſt of all the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes:</hi> yet <hi>Nemo illo minùs emax, nemo minùs aedificator,</hi> There was no man bought leſſe, no man built leſſe then hee. And withall take this caution with you of the wiſe <hi>Romane,</hi> That you doc euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more <hi>Finem omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rerum ſpectare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;


<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7797:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuperuacua deuitare,</hi> Looke vpon the end of all things, and auoide all ſuperfluities. For oftentimes theſe outward things are but the glorious monuments of inglori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and vngodly liues, of ſuch as had nothing elſe to commend them.</p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, they are ſuch parts of probity and honeſty, as reſpect others: and ſuch are ciuility in ſpeech, and compoſition of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, vibanity, fit and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable ſilence, ſhamefaſtneſſe and grauity, modeſty, gentleneſſe, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, placability, charity, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, liberality, friendſhip, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, truth, faith, thankfulneſſe. Theſe are the ribbes and bones, nay the very life and ſoule of goodnes; <hi>viz.</hi> the knowledge &amp; feare of God, prayer to God, and praiſe of God, ioyned with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of life and conuerſation towards our ſelues, and all other. <hi>Hic ſelus ſapit, aſt alij velut vmbra feruntur:</hi> The man that is thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed with goodnes, is the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7797:19"/>onely wiſe man; but all others paſſe away as doth a ſhadowe. This is the good deſired of man in my Text: this makes him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God and man, and makes him come neare to the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, <hi>Qui ſolus bonus, &amp; ipſa bonitas,</hi> Who is onely good, and goodnes it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Wee haue ſeene now what goodnes is. The next inquirie muſt be, why goodneſſe is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before greatneſſe, power, honour, riches, vnderſtanding, wiſedome, knowledge, and the like: or rather why this, and not any of them all elſe.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, this is deſired, and not they, becauſe there is no vſe of any of theſe, but by the hand and inſtruction of goodnes. Goodnes puts in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice all the greatneſſe, honour, riches, knowledge; and all the graces of God in vs, to the good of others: and whatſoeuer comes in her way, it directs them all, to the glory of God and good of others. It is like vnto fire, it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7797:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>makes all things like it ſelfe. It is the life of our graces: it puts ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into truth, that a man dare ſpeake it in the face of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt: ſo into knowledge, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, honour, riches, all which are but <hi>cadauera,</hi> dead carcaſſes, till goodneſſe in-ſoule them. For none of theſe things are good, till they bee vſed to their proper ends for which they were giuen vs: namely, therewith to doe good vnto others. Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> goodnes is more eſſentiall and connaturall to man then any of theſe. For man hath an eſſentiall and naturall goodnes, but no eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall greatneſſe, honor, riches, knowledge, and the like. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as one deepe calles another, ſo the goodnes of man calles for goodnes againe of man. Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> goodnes is more rare then great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, honour, riches, and the reſt: and <hi>Omnia rara chara,</hi> All rare things are deare and much deſired. Therefore goodnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a ſtranger, being ſo rare
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7797:20"/>a diamond, is the more deſired. Fourthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Omnia appetunt bonum,</hi> All things doe deſire that which is good: that is, their end and perfection, and ſo conſequently, all that conducteth thereunto, and that is goodneſſe.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, goodnes is contrary to the nature of all other things. For in the purſuite of all other things wee are limitted with conditions, which makes vs the more greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow them, <hi>Nitimur in veti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſemper, cupimuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> negata;</hi> We ſtriue againſt the ſtream, &amp; deſire things moſt that are denied vs: but this duty of goodnes is not limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at all, &amp; yet euery man deſires it, as if it were forbidden him. Sixtly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> goodnes appertaynes to the appetite and will; wiſdome, knowledge, truth, and the like, to the vnderſtanding: and God labours firſt to get the will to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline and deſire goodnes.<note place="margin">Phil. 2</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore worketh in vs both the will and the deed, firſt the will, and then the deed will followe. The
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7797:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>reaſon is, for that Sathan labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth firſt, to get and poſſeſſe the will, and therefore propoſed to the woman the principall good,<note place="margin">Gen. 3</note> euen God, who is goodnes it ſelfe: <hi>Eritis ſicut dij,</hi> Yee ſhall be as Gods. Therefore ſecing this perſwaſion wrought ſo much, the Lord labours heere, by ſercing goodnes before all other things, to giue vs that aſſuredly, which Satan promiſed lyingly. If you performe goodnes: <hi>Eritis ſicut dij,</hi> You ſhall be as Gods. Hence it is, that nothing can denominate a man according to his moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable title, <hi>viz.</hi> to bee called and bee a good man, nay a man, but onely goodnes. For hee is not a good man, that hath a good vnderſtanding and great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and wiſedome, nor he that is in great honour and reſpect, nor hee that hath great riches and poſſeſſions, but onely hee that poſſeſſeth goodnes: that is, hee that imployes all theſe to the good of others. Nay, hee is no
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7797:21"/>man that hath all theſe, if he want this goodnes of my Text.</p>
            <p>For as the Heathen <hi>Epictetus</hi> tels vs, wee try a man as wee try money. What figure or ſtampe hath this coine? <hi>Traianes?</hi> Then bring it. <hi>Neroes?</hi> Away with is, it is adulterate, ſophiſticate, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. So is it in the tryall of a man. What figure and ſtampe doe his purpoſes and practiſes carry? Is hee mercifull, meeke, humble, gentle, ſociable, patient, a louer of all men? Bring him, I allowe him, I admit him, and him onely for a man, and companion with God. But ſee hee haue not <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> characters, or <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars,</hi> or <hi>Ahabs,</hi> or <hi>Ieroboams.</hi> Is hee diſſolute, riotous, vaine, lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arious an vncleane perſon? Is he proud, haughty, high-minded? Is hee angry? Is hee a purſuer of enmities? Is hee froward? Doth hee reuenge himſelfe of ſuch as offend him, when hee gets oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity? Is hee an apparent impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent wicked liuer in any groſſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7797:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſinne? What then? Wilt thou ſay this is a man? Surely no. <hi>Quiduis potius quàm homo;</hi> He is rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing then a man: but a man hee is not. Wilt thou ſay, that all things are iudged of by their formes? If that bee ſo, then thou mayeſt call a lumpe of waxe or clay an apple, becauſe it is round like an apple: thou mayeſt ſay, it hath the ſmell and taſte of an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But the outwarde circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription and attendants are not ſufficient; it is not a noſe, or an eye, or the like, that are ſufficient to conſtitute a man: For humane purpoſes, and vertuous and noble actions, are required to make a man. This man heares not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome admonitions when he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, he vnderſtands not the things that belong to his peace, to his ſaluation: ſhall wee ſay he is a man,? No, hee is an aſſe: his ſhamefaſtneſſe and modeſty is dead, hee is vnprofitable, hee is any thing rather then a man. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother there is, who ſeekes with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7797:22"/>whom hee may quarrell, whom hee may ſpurne and contemne. Therefore is neither a ſheep nor an aſſe. What then? <hi>Fera beſtia,</hi> A wilde, bruite, ſauage beaſt? It is not then the ſhape &amp; image of a man that makes a man, but the image of God in man, his vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inclinations, and reſolute ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutions of good purpoſes. If he haue the ſtamp of vertue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, of mercy and goodnes, he is a man; if not, he is ſo much leſſe then a man, as a good man is more then a beaſt. If this were truely diſgeſted, it would make thouſands of ſuch as onely carry the names and ſhapes of men, to be much aſhamed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For what ſhould make the profane and godleſſe perſons of the world, who will not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with goodnes at all, to bluſh, if this doe not? That wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they thinke themſelues to bee the onely braue men of this world, they are in true account with God himſelfe) who is <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7797:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>rerum aeſtimator,</hi> The beſt iudge of all things) and alſo with all good men, eſteemed as the dung of the ſtreetes, and as ſalt that hath loſt his ſaltneſſe, which is good for nothing but to bee troden vnder foot.</p>
            <p>The Prodigall is a true em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of a voluptuous, impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent man, turned out of the nature of man into a ſwine and brute beaſt. For Chriſt tels vs, hee was ſet to feede ſwine. And to feede is vſually taken to recreate and delight: <hi>Oculos pictura paſcit inani,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virg.</note> Hee fed his eyes in beholding a vaine picture. So that to feede ſwine, is as much,<note place="margin">Ambr.</note> as by the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of ſinnes to delight and feed diuels: ſinne beeing truely the diuels food:<note place="margin">Ierom.</note> drunkenneſſe, vncleaneſſe, luxurie, and all other vices (in the opinion of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) no better but the diuells dainty diſhes:<note place="margin">Aug. Beda.</note> All of vs ſo long feeding ſwine, as we doe by our ſinnes pleaſe the diuell, or doe ſuch things as the diuell reioiceth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7797:23"/>at. For as the meate of Chriſt is to doe his Fathers will,<note place="margin">Io. 4</note> ſo it is the diuels meate, to doe his will.</p>
            <p>And therefore our Sauiour might well call the impenitent vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious vngodly man a ſwine,<note place="margin">Mat. 7</note> not fitte to haue pearles caſt before him: for as from the ſwine comes no good, neither milke as from the cow, nor wooll as from the ſheepe, nor faithfull ſeruice as from the dogge, nor obedience as from the horſe, nor bearing of burdens as from the aſſe, nor til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage as from the oxe: as the ſwine giues no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentment to him that feeds it, as the horſe doth by his pace, the dogge by his hunting, the hawke by his fowling: ſo the voluptuous carnall man is good for nothing; neyther hath God, who filles his bellie with his infinite treaſures daily, any pleaſure in him, or ſeruice from him.</p>
            <p>So that the wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſinner lying in his ſtinking pleaſures, is truely a ſwine wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7797:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the filthy puddle, as a filthy as aſwine, as gluttonous as a ſwine, delighting in dirt as a ſwine, not ſmelling the ſtinke of his ſin any more then the ſwine doth the ſtinke of the dirt it wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes in. And yet no dung ſtinks ſo much in our noſtrels, as ſinne doth in the noſtrels of God. And therefore the Scripture ſpeaking of impenitent ſinners,<note place="margin">2. King. 9</note> tels vs that the carcaſſe of <hi>Iezabel</hi> ſhould be as dung on the ground; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had ſinned againſt the Lord,<note place="margin">Zeph. 1</note> their fleſh ſhall bee as the dung: the wicked becoming as the dung of the earth.<note place="margin">Pſa. 81</note> Whereby we vnderſtand, that no hot ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king dung, or filthy ſtinking car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſe caſt out into the chanell, is ſo odious to our ſight and ſmell, as the impenitent ſinner is in the ſight &amp; noſtrels of God and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. And ſo foule is the ſtinke of infull ſoules,<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> as a godly Father obſerues, that therefore Chriſt at the laſt iudgement ſhall ſhake them off with that irreuocable,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7797:24"/>depart from me, as not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to endure their ſmell, no not ſo long as they ſhall bee a iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And as the vngodly are ſwine in theſe reſpects, ſo as Swine are choaked with the ſmell of roſes, as they chew not their meate, as they are vnrofitable for all ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſuch are the voluptuous and carnall men for all the world; to heare or ſee any good or godly thing doth choake them, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ruminate and conſider the Law of God, they are good for no worke of piety or religion, hauing no more Soule then ſwine haue,<note place="margin">Hor.</note> 
               <hi>Corpus ſine pectore,</hi> a Body without a Soule, following onely the good things that belong to the body, as ſwine doe, being fed and fatted for Hell, as ſwine for the ſhambles,<note place="margin">Tibul.</note> 
               <hi>Telluris inutile pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> an vnprofitable burden to the Earth,</p>
            <p>And is not the iudgement of all the learned Fathers the ſame concerning impenitent ſinners! Doth not one ſay,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> that Chriſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7797:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpeaks not in the Goſpell of ſwine, when he ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> Caſt not pearles before Swine, but of men who are of ſwiniſh manners, who like Swine wallow in the ſinke of ſinne? For as Swine are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally vncleane, ſwallowing the moſt filthy things, ſeeking foode for no other ende, then to fil their bellies, profitable for no one thing whilſt they doe liue, ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly are all filthy and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane perſons, all impenitent ſinners, they wallow in the filth of their owne ſinnes, ſwallow all the filthy dregges of iniquity, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low only after the foode that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth, are profitable forno good worke, nor haue any hope of a better life. Another ſaith,<note place="margin">Theoph.</note> What other thing are Chriſtians, that are giuen to carnall and filthy pleaſures, but Swine? Are not all they Swine that wallow in the filth of their vile naturall delights as ſwine doe in the mire? Can the eyes of ſwine looke vp to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen-wards, being framed as they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7797:25"/>are, to look downwards? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rightly are all ſinners, who with all their bodies, their mouthes, their hearts, their feete and hands are occupied in earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, no better then Swine, and bruite beaſts. The very Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphick and repreſentation of an vncleane, and diſhoneſt man,<note place="margin">Piernij</note> (amongſt the Learned) was a ſwine wallowing in the dirt and mire, and trampling ſweete ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vnder his feete: wicked men delighting more in the ſinke of their ſenſuality, then in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable ioyes of Heauen. Thus we ſee that the impenitent ſinner, of what kinde ſoeuer, is no better then a Swine and bruite beaſt. From which ground two obſeruations may fitly bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred,
<list>
                  <item>1. That they are not all men, that carry the faces and ſhapes of men.</item>
                  <item>2. That in all conditions of men, there are infinite who are very ſwine and bruite beaſts in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7797:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>their preſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that al are not men, that by their faces, ſhapes and habits ſceme ſo to be, but for the moſt part, are by their ſinnes become ſwine and bruite beaſts, men in name and ſhew, but not in deede and truth, is ſo pregnant a point, that the very heathen do witnes it. There are certaine men, ſaith <hi>Tully,</hi> not men indeede, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in name: borne men in-deede, but by their ſinnes haue made themſelues beaſts: and <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſeeing an effeminate young man, ſaid, it was a ſhame for him to make himſelfe worſe then Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had framed him, for Nature had made him a man, but he had made himſelfe a woman; but if he had ſeene our times, he would rather haue blamed men, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themſelues beaſts. I would but know this of any graue and ſober man, whether I were to be reprooued for calling a proud, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous, bloudy man, a Lyon?<note place="margin">Pro. 28.</note> Doth not the wiſe king call a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7797:26"/>wicked ruler ouer the poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, a roaring Lyon, and hungry Beare?<note place="margin">Syr. 4</note> Doth not the wiſe man aduiſe not to be a Lyon in a mans owne houſe, beating his ſeruants for his fantaſie? Doth hee not ſay,<note place="margin">Syr. 13.</note> that as the wilde Aſſe is the Lyons prey, ſo are poore men the meate of the rich? And what if I ſhould call a litigious and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome man, that is euer biting &amp; barking at other mens works, a Dog?<note place="margin">Phil. 3</note> Doth not the Apoſtle, call all euill workers Dogs? doth not Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſay, that without, that is, in Hell are Dogs; that is, inchaunters,<note place="margin">Apoc. 22.</note> whoremongers, murderers, Idolaters and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer loueth or maketh lies? Doth not Chriſt himſelfe call <hi>Herod</hi> a Foxe?<note place="margin">Luc. 13.</note> Goe and tel that Foxe. And doth hee not commaund to take the Foxes, the little Foxes that deſtroy the vines, namely, all dangerous Heretiques,<note place="margin">Can. 2</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauſhed liuers that wound and rent and ſcandalize his Church?</p>
            <p>And what if I call thoſe ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7797:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>and dull in the waies of God, Aſſes? thoſe ſcornefull and proud pecocks, borſes, that neigh vnder euery one that ſitteth on them?<note place="margin">Syr. 33</note> Thoſe wauering and inconſtant, graſhoppers? Thoſe that wallow in the filth of their luſts, ſwine? How can we eſteeme him that is transformed with vices,<note place="margin">Boet.</note> to bee a man? If he doe greatly thirſt after riches, he is like the wolfe: If hee bee cruell, vnquiet, he is like the Dog: if he be ſubtile and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, hee is like the Foxe: If an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, like the Lyon; If fearefull, like the Hart: If ſlow and heauy, like the Aſſe; if light and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, like the birds; if drowned in the vncleane filth of his luſts, he is like a Swine wallowing in the mire. Yea, euen the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (as ſome obſerues) calls ſome men by the name of beaſts,<note place="margin">Chry.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their perturbations and vices. And how can wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude otherwiſe then that men are changed into Beaſts, when forſaking reaſon, they take to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7797:27"/>themſelues vnreaſonable appetits, and deſites?<note place="margin">ſer. 5.</note> are they not like hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes euery man neihing after his neighbours wife?<note place="margin">Math. 3</note> Are they not generations of vipers, that are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenciouſly wicked and vicious? Surely whoſoeuer is ouercome with beaſtly pleaſures, is iuſtly by the wiſe,<note place="margin">Aul. gell.</note> accounted in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of beaſts and ſauage crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Euen this little paſſion of loue,<note place="margin">Tere.</note> carnall loue, will ſo change a man,<note place="margin">Mant.</note> that one would ſcarce know him to be the ſame. <hi>Fit pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus omnis amans,</hi> ſaith the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Dum pro ratione ltbido,</l>
                  <l>Iudicium nutu temperat omne ſuo.</l>
                  <l>Quiſquis enim viuit ſine lumine mentis &amp; vſu,</l>
                  <l>Fert hominis vultus, ingeniumque Ferae.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt luſt inſteede of reaſon diſtempers his iudgement, at his owne beck; euery one that loues, becomes a beaſt. For, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doth liue without the light and vſe of his vnderſtanding,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7797:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>doth carry the countenance of a Man, but the nature of a ſauage beaſt. What other thing would <hi>Diogenes</hi> expreſſe, when at noone day, he ſought a man in the open market place before all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple crying out, <hi>Hominem quaero, hominem quaere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diog. Laert.</note> I ſeeke a man, I ſeek a man. Or as another reports, that after hee had often in a publique place cryed, <hi>Heus homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> Hoe ye men, and many men comming to him, he droue them away with his ſtaffe, ſaying, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, non purgamenta vocaui,</hi> I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for men, and not for dirty dunghills. What other thing, I ſay, meant hee, then to intimate that vicious perſons were no men, albeit they carried the ſhapes of men? For euery thing is not the ſame it appeares to be. Mariners ſayles are not therefore black, becauſe they ſeeme ſo to them that ſtand on the ſhoare: Nor are the Oates broken or crooked becauſe the one halfe being in the water, and the other
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7797:28"/>out, they ſeeme ſo to be: Nor are Apples therefore the greater, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe looking on them in a glaſſe obliquely, they ſeeme ſo: Nor yet is the Sunne ſo ſmall as it ſeemes, nor ſo ſlow in his motion, as to the eye it appeares: So neyther is all Gold that gliſters, nor eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one a Man, that ſeemes to be a Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> was <hi>Iacob,</hi> and not <hi>Eſau,</hi> albeit hee was cloathed with his garments, and his neck lapt in a Goates skinne. If euery thing that carries the ſhape of a thing,<note place="margin">Pli.</note> were the ſame thing, then the beaſt of <hi>Aethiopia</hi> called <hi>Mantichora</hi> ſhold be a Man, becauſe it hath the face and cares of a Man, and ſpeakes as a man. Then <hi>Syrens, Satyres,</hi> water Nimphs, and many fiſhes, and Faunes ſhould be men and women, ſeeing they carry the ſhapes of men. Then <hi>Harpyies</hi> ſhould be called Virgins, becauſe they haue Virgins faces; then a painted man, ſhould bee a very Man, and the <hi>Crocodile</hi> ſhould be
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:7797:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>a man, becauſe it ſheds teares as a Man; and ſo an Ape which much reſembles a man in nimbleneſſe and geſtures, ſhould be a Man. But as the Poet ſpeakes of Syre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Satyres, Faunes, Nimphs and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miaes,
<q>
                  <l>Si videas vultus, homines vidiſſe putabis:<note place="margin">Mant.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Eſſe feras conſtat, ſi intuearis opus.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If you looke on their counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, you would iudge them to be men: but if you looke on their workes and action, they will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be very beaſts. So ſay I of all carnall, ſenſuall, licentious perſons; if yee behold their faces, and perſons, they are men in ſhape: but looke into their liues and actions, you ſhall finde them very bruite beaſts. It is not forme alone that will guide our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For then we may call any round apple of Gold, an Apple, and ſay it hath the ſmell and taſte of an Apple, the outward appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is not enough; to haue a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7797:29"/>noſe and eyes, is not ſufficient to the conſtitution of a Man, reaſon and iudgement, goodneſſe and piety is alſo required. And as all ase not kings that weare pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple roabes, Scepters, and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dems of kings; nor all daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that repreſent the perſons of daughters. (for <hi>Hercules</hi> ſpun in the company of his <hi>Omphale</hi> in the habit of a Woman, and valiant <hi>Achilles</hi> conuerſed in a Virgins habit amongſt the daughters of <hi>Lycamedon,</hi> and yet for all that were men and no women,) ſo no more are all that carry the faces and habits of men, to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted men, as all in ſheeps cloathing are not ſheepe. But a poore man is ſtill a poore man, albeit clad in princely roabes, and a woman is a woman albeit in the habit of a Man; the wolfe is ſtill a wolfe though in ſheepes cloathing. No more doth the face and ſhape of a Man, make a Man, ſeeing our bodies are nothing elſe, but the garments of the Soule, and the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7797:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>body makes not a man, but the reaſonable inward Soule: ſo that if he be a Man, he is a reaſonable Soule, and if he be a reaſonable Soule, he is a Man; but if he haue a beſtiall, and a ſenſuall Soule, then is he but an apparition and ſhadow of a Man, falſely carrying the Image and ſhape of that hee is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not the thing that is ſeene, ſaith diuine <hi>Plato.</hi> We are one thing, ſaith a Father, and the things that are outs are another thing,<note place="margin">Ambr.</note> and the things that are about vs, and belong vnto vs, are another thing. Wee are the Soule and vnderſtanding; and more we are not. So that whoſoeuer is drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the filthy puddles of this World, is no more participant of reaſon then a bruite beaſt, and rather a man in name then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doede.</p>
            <p>Seeing then the dominion of ſin doth turne man into a beaſt, what is it that will make one truely and indeede a Man? Is it
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7797:30"/>reaſon? Surely no, vnleſſe it bee ſanctified reaſon. Is it the faculty of ſpeaking? no neither. For the <hi>Hyena,</hi>
               <note place="margin">li.</note> and <hi>Mantichora</hi> can ſpeak like a Man. What then? Surely, if that learned writer may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued,<note place="margin">Lact.</note> it is onely the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the diuinity, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, that makes a man, and giues the true difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and all other things: for take away Religion, and then neyther wiſedome nor iuſtice can be kept, ſeeing the vnderſtanding of the diuinity, whereby we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from beaſts, is onely found in Man.<note place="margin">Plut.</note> So the heathen man could iudge, that it was a wicked and ſtrange thing, to aſcribe reaſon to thoſe things; that wanted the knowledge of God. Therefore where I finde no ſparke of true reaſon, no words worthy to come from a Man, no foot-ſteps of Religion, piety, goodneſſe, and the knowledge of God (the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary markes and badges of a Man.) If I ſhall deny him to bee
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7797:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>a man, I doe him no iniury, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my text tels me that <hi>goodneſſe is that which is required of euerie man;</hi> neither doth the definition of a man agree to him, and ſo hee cannot be a man.</p>
            <p>Beſides, if hee that outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alone repreſenteth a man, bee not a man, what is hee then? Whatſoeuer liues aboue a vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue life, muſt either be a God, an Angell, a man, or beaſt. But men that liue wickedly are no Angels, much leſſe are they Gods. And ſeeing iniquity and ſin hath caſt them downe belowe the condition of man, it muſt needes follow they are no men; but car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying about with them bodies, without reaſonable and religious ſoules, it neceſſarily followes, that they are bruite beaſts. And ſo it comes to paſſe,<note place="margin">Boet.</note> as one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, that who forſaking pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity and honeſty, leaues off to be a man, when he can by no means paſſe into the diuine ſtate &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, hee is turned into a beaſt.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:7797:31"/>And in this reſpect was it that the Prophet ſayd,<note place="margin">Iſ. 50</note> Wherefore came I, and there was no man? Why not a man? Becauſe as one ſaith on this place,<note place="margin">Ierom.</note> Euery man for ſaking the image of God, makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like the beaſts and ſerpents. And who knows not, that for this cauſe the Prophet admired that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhould bee ſo populous,<note place="margin">Lam. 1</note> and yet bee alone and forſaken? How doth the City remayne ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary, that was full of people? But what is this the Prophet ſpeakes? Hath ſorrow ſwallowed vp his ſenſes? If ſhee bee full of people, how is ſhee alone? If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, how is ſhee full of people? Yes, there were many faces and bodies of men, but not one true man, not one reaſonable man, not one godly man,<note place="margin">Pſal. 14</note> not one reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious man: All were gone out of the way, they were altogether become abhominable, there was none that did good, no not one. Thus was the Citty full, and yet ſolitary, not one good man, or
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:7797:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>very few to bee found in it. If this be ſo, then furely the Prophet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes wicked and vicious perſons for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no more then we do. And for the ſame cauſe, the holy Ghoſt in the Scriptures ſtiles ſome men foxes, ſome dogs, ſome ſwine, ſome wolues, ſome lions, ſome ſerpents, and the like.<note place="margin">Iſ. 11 Iſ. 59 Dan. 7 Luk. 13 Can. 2 Acts 20 Apoc. 22</note> Thus is the prouerbe verified, <hi>Homo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minilupus,</hi> One man is a wolfe to another. Thus did the godly Martyr <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſight with beaſts from <hi>Syria</hi> vnto <hi>Rome,</hi> at Sea and Land; day and night was hee bound with ten Leopards, that is, with ſouldiers that kept him, to bee tormented. May wee not reade that <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> called the <hi>Flagitious, Athenians,</hi> beaſts and ſheepe? And that <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſeeing a rich man one day walking in the market, called him a golden ſheepe? Did not all the Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts eſteeme that man to bee a beaſt, who beeing indued with reaſon, yet committed things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to reaſon? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7797:32"/>were they wonr to cry out, Hence beaſtly affections, hence, flye from mee ye capitall enemies of mine, leſt I ſhould be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to become vnruly &amp; beſides my ſelfe. What doe you heere, ye robbers of my better part? you theeues, that lay bolts and ſhac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles on my ſoule, that yee might domineere ouer that which was created to that end, that it might command the whole worlde? Haue you neuer read that golden ſentence, that hee ſeemes more beaſtly then any beaſt, who hath reaſon and vſeth it not? Doth not the reuerend ſcholler cite this out of <hi>Ariſtotle, Homo beſtialiter viuens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beda.</note> 
               <hi>eſt centies milleſies beſtia peior?</hi> A man that liues beaſtly, is an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand times worſe then a beaſt? For it is true which the wiſe Philoſopher ſpake,<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> Man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying the law, is the beſt of all liuing creatures; but ſeparate from the law and ruſtice, is the worſt of all others. Therefore the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Father affirmeth,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> that if man
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:7797:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>were ſuffered to liue as hee liſt, he would fall into outrages vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable. Wee may then ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of all this euidence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that all are not men which carry the ſhapes and habites of men; and that all voluptuous, carnall, impenitent ſinners, are no men, but beaſts in mens ſhape, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they want the goodneſſe in my Text.</p>
            <p>Secondly, out of this, will the ſecond obſeruation plainely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: namely, That in all condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, are infinite, who in their preſent eſtate, are no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ſwine and bruite beaſts, ſeeing they liue in infidelity, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency, and all kinde of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probity. For if theſe teſtimonies of Scriptures, Fathers, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Hiſtorians, and Poets, be truc; how many ſhall wee finde in euery ſtate and condition of men, that are ſwine, dogges, wolues, lions, vipers and ſcr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents? The forreſt of Arden, nor the woodes of Mormatane, doe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7797:33"/>afford acornes enough to giue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſwine one. And I know not whether the Heauens haue ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtars, the Sea ſo many grames of ſand, the Ocean ſo, many fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, fiſhes ſo many ſins, Fraunce ſo many grapes, the Alpes ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny flakes of ſnowe, or Hannony that Paradiſe ſo many flowers, as wee ſhall finde euery where men that are turnd ſwine, wolues, dogges, vipers, ſerpents, &amp; brutt beaſts.</p>
            <p>For vnto how many of all ſorts may it truely be ſayd, <hi>O curuae in terris animae, &amp; coeleſtium inanes?</hi> O crooked ſoules on earth, and voyde of heauenly things?<note place="margin">Pſa. 17</note> To how many may wee ſay, they turne their eye downe to the ground? neuer lifting vp ther eies to heauen, from whence all good comes to them, but like ſwine fee de on the Acornes, neuer look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp to the tree that bare the? Now, if you will take a liſt of them, and number them if you can; So many as I ſhall ſee to be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7797:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>delighted with the filthy puddle of carnall pleaſures, neither per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, hearing, or doing any thing that belongs to piety and godlineſſe, but onely to ſerue the time, ſo many muſt I iudge to be ſwine. O how many ſwine hath this worlde in opulent Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and glorious Courts of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Where men ſhould in great plenty be ſeene, euen there they play they ſwine and bruite beaſts. There is <hi>Circes</hi> turning men into ſwine. There is <hi>Epiourus</hi> that tame vncleane hogge. There are all kinde of beaſts innumerable, ſmall and great. As many as wee ſhall ſee hauing no more ſoule then a ſwine, <hi>Auimam pro ſale,</hi> Onely a ſoule to keepe the body from ſtinking &amp; rotting as beaſts haue, who neuer dreame of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life, where ſo ules are immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall: but liue as if there were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heauen nor Hell, (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts of our times:) ſo many ſwine &amp; beaſts wee may ſay there are. O good God, how doth the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7797:34"/>earth abound with ſuch kinde of ſwine? The ſow that farrowed thirty white pigges in the place Where <hi>Aeneas</hi> founded and built his City <hi>Alba,</hi> had neuer ſuch a plentifull litter, as Atheiſme and impiety at this day hath brought forth. Yea they are growen to that height of all iniquity, that they will wallowe in the mire without all controulment. Come, ſay they,<note place="margin">Sap. 2</note> let vs enioy the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that are preſent, for this is our lot, this is our portion. And ſhal I not think them to be ſwine, that cramme themſelues with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licates, till it come vppe againe? nothing commiſerating the poor me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſt, which by want or loſſes are driuen to extreame pouerty; no man remembring the afflictions of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> nor euer ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yeelding them wooll to cloath them, or milke to feede them, more then ſwine doe? But what talke I of ſwine? Theſe ſwine ſwim in all kinde of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, euen vnto ſurfeit; theſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7797:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſwine come not all to the ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, nor doe all of them accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> a ſhip-board. Theſe feede not in the farmes vnder the trees, they vſe not all one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſty, but euen famous Cities, goodly Countries, and glorious Courts of Kings, are full fraught with ſuch ſwine. That as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſayde,<note place="margin">Eccl. 12</note> there was no end in making bookes; ſo hauing in ſome ſort viewed this heard of ſwine, if we ſhould take an accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the other bruite beaſtes, to which the holy Ghoſt fitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares wicked, voluptuous, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent ſinners; I ſhould rather wearie you, then reckon them vp, there would bee no end in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring them. For as the Apoſtle ſayd to his fellow labourers,<note place="margin">Acts 20</note> that after his departure, grieuous wolues would enter, not ſparing the flock: So I may ſay, not only that the Heathen, but that all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of bruite beaſts, worſe then the heathen, are entred into the Lords inheritance,<note place="margin">Pſa. 79.</note> defiling his
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7797:35"/>holy Tempie, and making ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocke of all religion and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.<note place="margin">Pſa. 22</note> The fat Bulls of Baſan do encloſe the godly on euery ſide, the wilde Bores out of the wood doe ſtriue to roote vp that little vine of the godly, and the wilde beaſts of the field deuour it.<note place="margin">Pſa. 80 Pſa. 22</note> Gods dearlings are in the power of dogges, and in the mouthes of lions, they lye lurking in their dennes,<note place="margin">Pſa. 10 Ier. 9</note> and rauiſh the poore. The ſerpents and cocatrices that by corruption and oppreſſion ſting the godly to death, and will not bee charmed but with gifts, are euery where rife, Euery one turneth into this race,<note place="margin">Ier. 8</note> as the horſe into the battell. Like fed horſes euery one neigheth after his neigbours wife. Like wanton &amp; vntamed calues,<note place="margin">Ier. 31 Pſa. 58</note> they keepe no bounds. Like venomous ſerpents and deafe adders, they ſtop their eares and will not bee charmed, charme they neuer ſo wiſely. As a cage is full of birds, ſo are their houſes full of deceit,<note place="margin">Ier. 5</note> they are
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7797:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>waxen fatte and ſhining, they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerpaſſe the deeds of the wicked; they execute no iudgement, Shal I not viſit for theſe things, faith the Lord, ſhall not my ſoule bee auenged on ſuch a Nation as this?</p>
            <p>Here then I require two things to bee obſerued. Firſt, that wee woulde keepe the methode which God propoſeth in doing good: that is, that in euery of our actions, the goodneſſe to be done to others be aymed at. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that wee labour to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue goodnes and good men, by taking away the worme that kils them.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to keepe the order that God vſeth. For God preferres order before all things: and as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Bonum in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine conſiſt it,</hi> Good conſiſts in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Now this is Gods order, 1. To ayme at our good in all his actions. 2. As the ſame Father ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> it is Gods order to make <hi>Modus ſpecies et ordo, generalia bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:7797:36"/>Meaſure, forme and order, to bee generall good things in all his creatures. So that, <hi>Vbi haec tria magna ſunt, magna bona ſunt; vbi parma, parua bona ſunt; vbi nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, nullum bonum eſt;</hi> Where theſe three are great, there are great good things; where little, little good things; where none, no good thing at all. Looke then if the end of all your actions bee the good of others: looke if you finde theſe three good things in your actions, which God hath put in euery creature: meaſure, forme, and order. Meaſure that temperately, forme that decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, order that diſcreetly all things bee done. If ſo, then doe you followe Gods methode in doing good. But alas we run contrary, and vtterly deſtroy Gods order. For what meaſure is it to poure water into ſieues, or rent diſhes, that ſpend it faſter then they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it? What forme is there to rewarde dogges for killing the game, and not iuſt and holy men
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:7797:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>for killing of vices? What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is there in our monſtrouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and exceſſe of apparel? What forme, to caſt all honours and preferments vpon the vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, or in the loweſt ranke of ſeruice, and to neglect the beſt and worthieſt ſeruices? What or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what diſcretion, what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to runne greedily after the fooliſh vanities of this life, and neuer labor to purchaſe any ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for the Soule? Is not this Chriſts order, Firſt ſeek the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and the righteouſneſſe thereof?<note place="margin">Math. 6</note> Firſt thou ſhouldſt ſeeke, as that good Father ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Vt ſis bonus,</hi> that thou maiſt be good thy ſelfe; and then <hi>Vnde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias bonum,</hi> the things whereby thou maiſt do good to others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee muſt labour to preſerue goodneſſe and good men, by taking away the Canker that corrupts them. So then a weeding muſt be vſed: that wiſe Roman ſpake moſt truly,<note place="margin">Sen.</note> 
               <hi>Bonis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, qui malis parcit,</hi> He doth hurt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7797:37"/>the good that ſpares the quill. Therefore the magiſtrate muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be worming of the Land; and in that greate worke of purging the common-wealth, or refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming any houſe or Family, hee muſt euer haue reſpect to theſe three conſiderations, firſt, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him he puniſheth. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or that the puniſhment being exemplary, may make others the better. Thirdly, or that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked being taken out of the way, the godly may liue the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely. But he that will preſerue goodneſſe, muſt ſtill be lopping away the Canker boughs: For as that learned man ſaith well,<note place="margin">Lactan.</note> 
               <hi>Bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſalutem custodit, qui malos pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit,</hi> He that puniſheth wicked men, preſerues the ſafety of good men. To which that of the diuine Philoſopher doth well agree, <hi>Malitiae medicamentum eſt poena;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plato.</note> puniſhment is the beſt Phiſicke for malice and wickednes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hec that would heale a ſicke common-wealth, or a fainting
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7797:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>Family muſt miniſter <hi>Dauids</hi> phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke,<note place="margin">Pſal. 101</note> a wicked perſon muſt not dwell in his houſe. So <hi>Dauid</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his ſick kingdome and Court.<note place="margin">Antiſthenes</note> Hence the wiſe heathen reſolued, that it was the greateſt peſt of a common-wealth not to diſcerne the good from the bad: that is, to obſerue and aduance the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and neglect the iuſt and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous: For the goodneſſe of the ſubiects eſtabliſheth the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And their improbity ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines and ſubuerts it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that wiſe Roman concludes,<note place="margin">Cic.</note> that neyther houſe nor common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth can long ſtand, if rewards be not prouided for the good, and puniſhments for the wicked. We come into our gardens and orchards, and ſeeing them grown ouer with nettles and ſuch other traſh, preſently we fall to wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; pruning, and are offended with thoſe that ſhould haue the care of it, that it is not done, leſt we ſhould loſe the benefit of the fruite: and ſhall we not much
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:7797:38"/>more labour to keepe the garden of the Church and kingdome from the Nettles and weedes of impiety and wickedneſſe, which will at length choake the growth of all goodneſſe in the Land? But alas, what fruite can we expect, when not only briers and thiſtles are ſuffered to grow vp, but are more cheriſhed then the good and wholeſom hearbs themſelues? What happineſſe may we look for, when the herbs are eyther pluckt vp by the roots, or at leaſt, ſo ſpite-blaſted, and neglected, that they wither and dye for want of plucking vp the weedes of vices that ouertoppe them?</p>
            <p>The third inquiry is:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> How goodneſſe ſhould be ſo deſired of all, and ſo little practiſed of any. Firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſhall I ſay, it is like the little book which <hi>Iohn</hi> tooke and cate,<note place="margin">Apoc. 10</note> and it was in his mouth as ſweet as honey, but made his belly bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? So goodneſſe, is a ſweete ſubiect to be ſpoken of, but bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:7797:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be practiſed; euery man can reliſh it with his mouth, but few can diſgeſt it in their hearts, and fewer practiſe it with their hands.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Or ſhall I ſay that as goodneſſe doth commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate it ſelfe to all, ſo it hath a magneticall attractiue power, to draw all to the gaze of it? the face of goodneſſe being ſo beautifull, that the moſt prophane man in the World, would die to bee but dyed in her colours, and cloathed with her honourable titles. Euen prophane <hi>Balaam</hi> would gladly die the death of the righteous, and caſt-away <hi>Saule</hi> would be honoured and reputed good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prophet. But becauſe they deſire the name and not the thing, therefore they are but in a dreame, and imbrace a ſhadow. Or thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſhall I ſay, for that it is the onely ſhelter of impiety? For vnder the couert of goodneſſe, walke all kinds of impurity and impiety: <hi>Tuta frequenſque via eſt, per amici fallere nomen:</hi> It is a ſafe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:7797:39"/>and common courſe to deceiue vnder pretence of friendſhip. So vnder the cloake of goodnes and Religion, is all miſchiefe pallia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and vizarded. And it is one of the moſt dangerous enemies, that goodneſſe and good men haue;<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> for as that holy Father ſaith <hi>Malum ſub ſpecie boni celatum, dune non cognoſcitur, non cauctur,</hi> When euill doth maske vnder the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of good, being not known, it cannot be preuented. Or fourthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſhall I ſay, that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe makes all men that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it diminiſh their goods, and come to the contempt of the world? that thoſe which haue wiues,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7</note> be as though they had none, thoſe that weepe as though they wept not, thoſe that reioyce as though they reioyced not; thoſe that buy, as though they poſſeſſed not, thoſe that vſe the world, as though they vſed it not, ſo that now they become as zealous as in the primitiue age, they haue all things common,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7797:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>and part to euery man hath need. And therefore becauſe men doe ſoe goodnes to be an ill husband,<note place="margin">Act. 2</note> and prodigal of her ſelfe and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, after a little experience of her, they ſhake her off, as not for their profit. Or laſtly ſhall I ſay, it is, becauſe there are ſo few exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of goodneſſe to prouoke vs? Surely euen for all theſe, is this happy duty of goodneſſe ſo much deſired of all, ſo little practiſed of any. For goodneſſe is bitter, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauory and diſtaſtefull to a carnal man. Euery man loues the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous name of it, but cares not for the thing it ſelfe: It is a good ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and cloake for impiety: It diminiſheth our ſubſtance and the things we loue deare, and hath few or no preſidents to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure vs to it. No wonder then, if ſo few affect it in the practiſe.</p>
            <p>So come we to examine the 4.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> &amp; laſt inquiſition of this duty. <hi>An ſit bonitas,</hi> whether there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good neſſe left in the World, any ſuch thing as goodneſſe is,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:7797:40"/>and where it may be found; there is ſuch barre nnes of goodnes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where, that we may well ſay of it, as the Lord did of <hi>Ieconiah:</hi> write this man childleſſe,<note place="margin">Ier. 22</note> a man that ſhall not proſper in his days. So we, that God hath bidden write our age deſtitute of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not ſhall goodneſſe proſper in our age: not for that <hi>Ieeoniah</hi> had no Son, did God commaund thus to write, for he had <hi>Salathiel,</hi> but becauſe he had but one Son, and the kingdome and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was departed from him. Nor doe I ſay this, for that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhal haue no iſſue, but becauſe ſhe ſhall haue very few children, and the kingdome and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is departed from them: they ſhall haue little or no honour, dignite or preferment in this world.</p>
            <p>The Prophet ſpake it long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 14</note> The Lord looked downe from Heauen, to ſee if any would vnderſtand and ſeeke after God: but they were all gone but of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:7797:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>way, there was none that did good, no not one. If he ſpake this with griefe of heart, I am ſure, I ſpeake it not without ſorrow. For what cauſe of ſorrow can be greater, when as we may iuſtly complayne with the good king, There is not one godly man left,<note place="margin">Pſal. 12</note> the faithfull are fayled from the children of men?</p>
            <p>In <hi>Noahs</hi> age all fleſh had cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted their wayes, and then the flood came and ſwept them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. In <hi>Abrahams</hi> time, there was no feare of God in the Land, and then God ſent fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone on <hi>Sodom</hi> and her three ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. In the time of the iudges, when there was no king in <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 17</note> euery man did what was good in his owne eyes, and then the people did eate vp one another. In the time of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> the faithfull City was become an harlot, they had not ſo much vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding as the Oxe and the Aſſe: then the Lord eaſed him of his aduerſaries, and auenged him of his enemies.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:7797:41"/>In <hi>Ieremies</hi> time,<note place="margin">Ier. 5</note> there was not a man in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that executed iudgement, and ſought the truth. Therfore a Lyon out of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſhall ſlay them, a Wolfe out of the wilderneſſe deſtroy them, and a Leopard watch ouer their Cities.<note place="margin">Pſal. 14</note> In <hi>Dauids</hi> time, there was none that did good, not one. Then came the wrath of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wealthieſt of them, and ſtrooke; downe the choſen men that were in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> In <hi>Salomons</hi> time,<note place="margin">Eccleſ 7.</note> but one man of a thouſand, (A thouſand to one we ſhall not finde one now) and then tenne Tribes were rent from his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.<note place="margin">1. King. 13</note> In <hi>Chriſts</hi> time, many were called and few choſen, and then came the deſolation of that moſt famous <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and vtter ſubuerſion of the people of God, ſuch as was neuer read of in any age, that the choſen generation ſhould be vagabonds and runa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates ouer the whole World to the end thereof. In <hi>Paules</hi> time, not many noble, not many wiſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:7797:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>according to the fleſh were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> nay, all ſought their owne, and not that which was Chriſts,<note place="margin">Phil. 2</note> and then the Church of God, was vnder gricuous perſecution; and when Chriſt comes,<note place="margin">Luc. 18</note> ſhall he finde faith on the earth? And why may not we ſpeake all theſe things of theſe our times, who haue added to the iniquities of all times? Why may not we feare the like iudgements, for the want of that goodneſſe, which want procured theſe iudgements? May not we ſay, there is not one that doth good? All fleſh hath cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted his way? There is no feare of God in the Land? Euery man doth that which is good in his owne eyes? The faithfull City is become an Harlot. Not one good man of a thouſand can be found. Surely, we haue filled vp the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our fathers iniquities, and if we ſpeedily repent not, God will fill vp the meaſure of his iudgements vpon vs for it.</p>
            <p>Here then I doe briefely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:7797:42"/>theſe two points. Firſt, that all ages haue had in all places a penury and want of goodneſſe, more or leſſe. Secondly, that no age euer eſcaped to be ſeuerely puniſhed for that want. Let <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum poena,</hi> be <hi>bonorum cautela;</hi> the puniſhment of the wicked, be the caution of the godly, <hi>Et aliena pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricula noſtra adminicula;</hi> other mens harmes and dangers, our inſtructions and helps.</p>
            <p>Goodneſſe (I confeſſe) is hard to be found in our age: the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practiſe is according to the common prouerbe, Euery man for himſelfe, and God for vs all. It is now euery mans ſtudy and care to gather riches, to grow great, to get honours, dignities and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours for themſelues and their poſterity; whilſt the common good, nor yet any others good, but their owne priuate, is aymed at. But indeede, how can they vſe goodneſſe that know not what it meanes? They are of that kinde of men of whom the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:7797:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49</note> Whilſt thou doeſt good to thy ſelfe, euery man will ſpeake good of thee. They know not, that the nature of goodneſſe is ſuch, that the good man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows himſelfe wholly, and what he hath, to the good of others, and yet is himſelfe neuer the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. As a thouſand candles may be lighted at one, and yet no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of light: So the good man communicates to all, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly that haue need of him, and yet hath no want: his riches, his wiſedome, his countenance, his labour, and ſo can ſay, <hi>Omnibus omnia factus ſum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9</note> I became all things to all men. Thus doth he after the example of God: who is therefore good, becauſe he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows on vs that be his children, what himſelfe is, and what he hath: therefore this is a true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, That he cannot be a good man, nor the childe of God, of what place ſoeuer he be, that loues himſelf and ſeekes his owne particular alone. The rule of that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:7797:43"/>learned Father is moſt true;<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Turpe eſt omnis pars quae ſuo toto noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruit:</hi> That part which agrees not with the whole, is a deformity to the whole. And ſeeing euery man is part of the kingdome wherein hee liues, it is impoſſible hee ſhould be a good man, that is not faſhioned to the Common good. Nor can the whole ſtand, if the parts be not well propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. Whence it is, that the Common good of a kingdome cannot thriue, if the greateſt part and namely, the greateſt men be not good men, and reſpectiue of the publike good. Therefore if any kingdome come to ruine, it is for want of this goodnes, that men doe not ſeeke the Common good, in which euery man hath his particular good.</p>
            <p>What was the cauſe the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Empire flouriſhed ſo long, and raigned as Queene and ſole Empreſſe of the world,<note place="margin">Val: Max:</note> but this (as the worthy Hiſtorian reports) that all ſtudied the Common
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:7797:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>good, and deſired rather to bee <hi>Pauperes in diuite imperto, quam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites inpaupere imperio;</hi> Poore in a rich Empire, then rich in a poore Empire? Thus came theſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then nearer that diuine precept then wee Chriſtians, Let no man ſeeke his owne,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10</note> but euery man anothers good. Good citizens muſt be like the Sun and Moone, they muſt ſhine vnto all. And thus is the Common-wealth made ſtable and laſting for euer. For if as the earth ſtands immooueable, becauſe euery parttends <hi>ad vnum,</hi> that is, to one point, which wee call the Center; ſo is a kingdome perdurable, when all ſeeke the Common good, and haue one Center and end in all their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>But alas, I might eaſily bee confined in ſpeaking of goodnes, either this that is the preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of kingdomes, or that which is the life and ſoule of families: not onely that there is ſo little goodneſſe in our times, but alſo
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:7797:44"/>for that the Scripture affords mee ſo little deſcant vpon the worde: which to mee is an euident argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the ſpirit of God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſawe, that towards the end of the world men would growe ſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, that the practice of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe would bee ſo precious and rare, as the name of it is ſeldome vſed in the Scriptures. For in the whole Booke of God, to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, as goodnes is aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to man, I onely finde it nine times recorded. Seauen times in the olde Teſtament, and three in the new.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. There is mention of the goodneſſe of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chr. 32</note> and it is ſay de that his goodneſſe was written in the Chronicles of the Kings of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Ioſias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chr. 35</note> and of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it is ſayde, that it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Chronicles too: to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate vnto vs, that the goodnes of Kings is fit to be chronicled for eternall memory, as a mytror to them that followe, becauſe there are ſo fewe examples of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:7797:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>goodneſſe amongſt great ones. In ſo much that of all the three and twenty Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſixe were good, <hi>Dauid, Aſa, Iehoſapbat, Ioas, Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Ioſias:</hi> But of all the Kings of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> there was neuer a good. Hence one ſayd wittily, that the names of all good Kings might be written in a ring. 3.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> There is a commandement; <hi>Fac bonitatem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 37</note> Be doing of good: and there is a ſingular rewarde annexed to it; verily thou ſhalt be fed. 4.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> There is mention of goodneſſe by the Prophet in theſe words:<note place="margin">Pſa. 38</note> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mee euill for good, <hi>Eo quod ſecter bonitatem,</hi> Becauſe I follow goodneſſe. Indeed goodneſſe is like an Owle, all the birdes fall vpon her: ſo if any man doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe goodnes in any proportion beyond the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort, they are ſure to be deſpiſed and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at euery hand. In <hi>Poters</hi> time it was true, who will harme you, if you ſeeke that is good?<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3</note> but now, Who will not harme
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:7797:45"/>you? an argument that there is little goodneſſe amongſt men. 5.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> My goodneſſe reacheth not vnto thee,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16</note> ſaith the good King, ſpeaking of God: that is, thou receiueſt no benefit from mee. If man of man and to man had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken this, it had beene moſt true in our age, for the moſt part; for as God receiues nothing from vs, ſo nor man, but what wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keepe from him.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. The wiſe King tells vs,<note place="margin">Pro. 19</note> that who poſſeſſeth vnderſtanding, loueth goodneſſe, therefore it ſeemes that our Age is a fooliſh Age, there is ſo little loue of goodneſſe.<note place="margin">Pro. 20</note> 7. The ſame King giues vs a taſte of euery mans vntoward diſpoſition to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes goodneſſe; Euery man will boaſt of his owne goodnes, but who can find a faithfull man? Wherein we ſee the louelineſſe of this grace, drawing euery man to chalenge her for his owne, but no man crauing to entertayne her. 8.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5</note> The Apoſtle names her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the fruites of the Spirit:
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:7797:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>but we ſhall haue much adoe to finde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, goodneſſe, in any ſpirit of our times. Laſtly, the ſame Apoſtle makes the fruite of the ſpirit to bee in <hi>Omni bonitate;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 5</note> In all goodneſſe: as if there were no fruite of the ſpirit of God in man, where goodneſſe doth not ſhew it ſelfe in a greate mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>And as it is in few places of the Scripture, ſo it is in few perſons of the worlde. I will not goe to the great ones,<note place="margin">Ier. 5</note> as the Lord doth to looke for this goodneſſe, and found the yoake broken, and the bonds burſt: nor to the Prieſts &amp; people, as the Prophet doth, to look for this goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Iſ. 24</note> &amp; found like Prieſt, like people; like ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, like maſter; like maid, like miſtreſſe; like buyer, like ſeller; like borrower, like lender; like giuer, like taker to vſury:<note place="margin">Ier. 8</note> no man repenting himſelf of his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſaying, what haue I done? but euery one turning to his race, as the Horſe ruſheth into the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:7797:46"/>I ſay, I will not goe thus farre: yet If I ſhould aske the Sea, it would ſay, goodneſſe is not in mee: if the Land, it would ſay, goodneſſe is not in mee: if I ſhould aske the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, it would ſay, goodneſſe is not in mee: if the Court, they would all confeſſe, that goodnes is not in them. So that if I call for goodneſſe, it is dumbe and ſpeakes not: if I cry for it, it is deafe and heares not: if I wiſh for it, it is lame and comes not: if I write of it, it is worne out of the world with writing: if I ſpeake of it, it is wearie of it: if I looke for it amongſt the dead, they will ſay, it is not yet borne: if amongſt the liuing, they will ſay, it died in its minority: if I looke for it with the olde, they are paſt it: if with the young, they are not yet come to it; if with the middle age, they will none of it: if with ſouldiers, it is againſt their valours: if with Courtiers, it is againſt their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: if with Lawyers, it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:7797:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>their profits. So that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing baniſhed from all ſorts and ſocieties of men, it is to bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">Apoc. 12</note> the fury of that great redde Dragon hath driuen it into the wilderneſſe with the woman: that is, the poore perſecuted Chur. of Chriſt, there to remaine not 1260. dayes, but yeares: if ſome good folke keepe it not out of the wilderneſſe, to be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant amongſt men, which for my part, I doe much deſpaire of.</p>
            <p>Yet will I not vtterly deſpaire to finde ſome prints of goodneſſe for all this ſcarcity: but in the ſearch of it, I am loth to ſpend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more time, ſeeing I haue bin ſo long time in the queſt of it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. Let euery man ſee what proportion of goodnes is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: but I feare, that a torch wil ſcarce finde a good man, ſuch as wee haue lim'd out, and ſuch as the Prophet hath pictured:<note place="margin">Pſa. 15</note> and yet ſo good muſt hee bee that will aſcend into the mountaine of Heauen. If then thou wilt gage
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:7797:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>thy goodneſſe, this is the way; looke how much thou profiteſt after euery Sermon thou heareſt, and ſo much as thou reformeſt thy life, ſo much is thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>They ſay, that a veſſell made of the Iuy tree, if water and wine be poured into it together, the wine will leake out, and leaue the water behinde it. Moſt mens hearts holde true reſemblance with this woode; for receiuing into them the wine of Gods worde, which ſhould inebriate them with the loue of God and goodnes, and alſo taking in the water of worldly apprehenſions, they leake out all the wine, and leaue nothing behinde but the pudled water of vanity, pride, ambition, luxurie, and ſuch other peſts of the ſoule. I muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate pardon in this my great li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of ſpeech: <hi>Inlibera ciuitate,</hi> ſayd that noble <hi>Octauianus, liberae debent eſſe linguae;</hi> In a free Citie euery mans tongue ſhould bee
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:7797:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>free, but much more in a free Church, and of a free man. For to ſpeake truely of our times, I cannot compare the men of it better then to a veſſell full of quickeſiluer, where all mettalls ſaue golde doe ſwimme, and that ſinkes to the bottome: So piety, religion, goodneſſe, and thoſe precious mettalls, without which wee can neuer attayne to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of goodneſſe, doe but float in the braines, and ſwimme in the vnderſtanding, they will not downe with vs Nothing wil ſink into our hearts but gold, nothing but gaines, and honour, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, will downe with vs.</p>
            <p>But ſome may obiect againſt this: that there muſt needes bee plenty of goodneſſe, ſeeing it is ſo little ſpent, for few or none do vſe it. I anſwere; that hath been the bane and ruine of this gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den myne of goodneſſe. For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the nature of all other mettalls and matters, it growes and encreaſeth by ſpending. The
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:7797:48"/>more prodigall man is of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the richer hee growes: if then thou wilt haue a treaſure, which cannot be exhauſted with ſpending, but growes and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the more, labour for goodneſſe, &amp; practice it: be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in profuſe and a ſpend thrift, and thou ſhalt growe moſt rich, moſt honourable. On the other ſide, ſpend it not, and thou art poore, naked, beggarly, miſerable, aboue all other men. A new found way to enrich and ennoble you: but yet the true found way: without which, no man ſhall euer enioy that happy and euer bleſſed eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Gods preſence. For the rule in Diuinity is moſt infallible:<note place="margin">Heb. 12</note> Follow peace with all men, and holineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee God: ſo goodneſſe and holineſſe muſt be followed, as a man followes his pleaſure or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: and ſpent as a liberall, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a prodigal man ſpends his ſubſtance, or elſe there is no ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God. Therefore let vs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayne
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:7797:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>that wiſe aduice:<note place="margin">Eccl. 11</note> Caſt thy bread vpon the waters; doe good to others, euen with the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard not onely of the loſſe of the thing, but euen with hazard and loſſe of thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And ſurely ſo many examples and actions of Gods goodnes to vs, ſhould mooue vs to this duty of goodneſſe, in imitation of him. The earth is full of his goodneſſe to vs. There is not a creature, but hath <hi>bonitas,</hi> goodneſſe, ingrauen in great Characters vpon it, to allure vs to goodneſſe: Beholde, <hi>Valde bona:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2</note> ſaith God vpon the reuiew of all his creatures; they were exceeding good. Which could neuer haue beene, but by the goodnes of God. But aboue all other his goodneſſes to vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnſpeakeable, he hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to vs the myſterie hid ſince the beginning of the world, the myſtery of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Chriſt Ieſus: beſides our peace, plenty, health, and many happy deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances and preſeruations, both ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:7797:49"/>and particular, hath he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vpon vs. O that he would be pleaſed to adde one goodneſſe more to theſe: that he would giue vs a meaſure of goodneſſe to make the true vſe of theſe his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite goodneſſes to vs, and to walke in ſome meaſure worthy of his goodnes. Surely his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to vs calls for our goodnes, ſeeing he makes all his creatures good to vs, to draw and allure vs to goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now if we haue not this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to beſtow all the benefites and bleſſings of body and minde, wherewith God hath inriched vs, to his glory, and good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; then we are not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of all the creatures, but alſo want the true vſe of them; nay, they are but al beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs to our infinite hurt and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. For moſt true is that which the wiſe Roman concludes:<note place="margin">Sen.</note> 
               <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil tibi bonum, ſine te bono:</hi> There is nothing in the World can bee good to thee, except thou thy
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:7797:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſelfe be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good. Therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, for euery goodneſſe of his beſtowed on thee, ſhall be accounted for how it hath beene imployed to the good of others.</p>
            <p>Thus come wee to the ſecond pillar of my Text,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the generality of the requiſition of this duty. For therefore it is ſaid in the Text, A man; becauſe no man is exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from this duty as our Sauiour ſaith in another caſe, that I ſay to one, I ſay to all, watch: ſo that which is deſired of one, is deſired of all, goodneſſe; and the more goodneſſe that any hath receiued from God, the more is he bound to ſhew to others. If fiue talents be receiued, fiue muſt be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for: If three, then three; If but one, then one: All muſt be imployed to the maſters benefite: nothing muſt be lapt vp in a napkin, leſt the reward of the idle and vnprofitable ſeruant fall to our lot, which was to bee bound hand and foote, and caſt
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:7797:50"/>into eternall fire.</p>
            <p>The Philoſophers ſay, that <hi>Ens &amp; bonum conuer tuntut:</hi> beeing &amp; good, are conuertible tearms. So that there is nothing in the world but it is good: and there is no good, but hath a being; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou haſt a being, and be a man, thou muſt haue goodneſſe, elſe thou looſeſt the name and being of a man: but this good which they ſpake of, is but a good of thy nature, not a good of grace. And thou muſt labor if euer thou wilt haue a being in Heauen, to get this good of grace, this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my text.</p>
            <p>This text is ſuch a body of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity, that in the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture there can ſcarce be any found to match it. For as goodnes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines all our duties, to God, to man, to our ſelues, to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, &amp; to all the creatures,<note place="margin">Pro. 12</note> (for a righteous man regards the life of his beaſt;) ſo it ſpeakes to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man in the world: for this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is deſired of euery man; no
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:7797:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>man can ſay, it appertaines not to me, for it is ſaid indefinitely, that, That is to be deſired of a man, is his goodneſſe; not of this or that man; but of euery man. So that here I might examine and enforce this duty vpon euery particular man, and euery particular calling in the world, ſeeing none are freed from it.</p>
            <p>There is no creature in the world that is ſo indigent and needy as man: For he ſtands in neede of the Sunne, the fire, the water, the ayre, the earth, and all the creatures to helpe him. Whence he ſhould take examples to compaſſionate the neceſſities of others, ſeeing all things ſince the creation neuer ceaſe to helpe our neceſſities. The learned doe ſay, that <hi>Bonum eſt ſui diffuſiuum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dioniſ.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſummu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonum, ſumme communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiuum:</hi> Good doth euer diffuſe and ſpread it ſelfe abroade: and the chiefe good, which is God himſelf, doth aboue other things chiefely diffuſe and communicate
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:7797:51"/>his goodneſſe to others: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the creatures are as ſo many goodneſſes of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to vs, therefore they all labour to helpe the neceſſities of others, as we ſee the Heauens, the Sea, the Elements. Now ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of them do ſo much fauor man, as that without their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to him, he could not liue, how much rather ſhould euery man labor by all meanes to helpe man?<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> The Philoſopher calls man the little world, the epitome and abridgement of the world, in whom the epilogue and ſumme of all the world is contayned, Therfore ſeeing man hath in him vertually all creatures,<note place="margin">Sap. 1</note> let him from them take example to work as they doe worke. If he haue the Sunne in him, let him doe as the Sunne: warme euery man; helpe euery mans neceſſity: if he haue the Earth in him; let him doe as the Earth doth, which nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ſuſtayneth all liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Let all the creatures be his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:7797:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſchoole-maſters vnto goodneſſe. For all are made to do him good, and he is made to doe euery man good. <hi>Hemo homini Deus, non daemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> Man muſt be to man a God, &amp; not a diuell: do him all good, but no harme. I ſhould neuer haue done in this point, if I ſhold inforce this duty vpon euery particular man, therefore I will reſtraine my ſelfe, to theſe two obſeruations. Firſt, that euery man muſt know, there is a generall duty of goodnes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him. Secondly, that particular men haue perſonall and particular duties of goodneſſe to be expected from them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſeuerall functions and places. Firſt, for the generall duty: the Prophet expreſſeth it in foure words:<note place="margin">Mich. 6</note> Hee hath ſhewed thee O man, what is good, and what the Lord requireth of thee: ſurely to do iuſtly, to loue mercy, to humble thy ſelfe, and walke with thy God. Firſt the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of righteouſneſſe is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of euery man to good rightly,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:7797:52"/>&amp; iuſtly to euery man. He muſt be in all his wayes as ſtraight &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right as the Fytre tree, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly without any knot growes vp towards Heauen, without bowing a bayre from a moſt ſtraight line. <hi>Iob</hi> is commended for ſuch a iuſt and vpright man. Secondly, the goodneſſe of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is required of him. For <hi>Bonum eſt ſui communicatinum:</hi> Good will diſperſe and communicate it ſelf. We ſee that trees doe not beare fruite for themſelues, but for the benefit and good of others: and a good man out of the good trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his heart, bringeth forth good things; ſo out of the good treaſure of his hands, he miniſters to the neceſſities of others. He is mercifull, liberall, and lendeth, he hath diſperſt abroad, and the prayſe of him endureth for euer. The <hi>Samaritane</hi> in the Goſpell, was ſuch a mercifull man. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the goodneſſe of Humility is required of him: without which there is no entrance into ioy. God
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:7797:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>giues grace onely to the humble.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5</note> He muſt ſtoupe that will come in at the low gate of Heauen; if he be neuer ſo well furniſhed with other graces, and want this, his portion ſhall be with hypocrites, and vnbeleeuers. Fourthly, the goodnes of obedience or dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is required. No Idle by comes to Heauen. He that will come there muſt euer be walking the way that leades to it: it is a long iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and cannot be performed in leſſe time then a mans whole life. And well may he walke to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen who hath God <hi>Socium itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> to walke with him. If man will walke with God, walke as he hath walked, walke as he hath taught him, and as he doth guide him, he ſhall neuer fayle to come moſt happily to his iournies end.</p>
            <p>Such a walking man was <hi>Enoch.</hi> By the continuall motion of the Heauens, all creatures are ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and doe liue, without which motion, they could not eyther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe or continue: So by our
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7797:53"/>motion &amp; walking with God all his graces are beginner in vs to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by that walking do liue in vs and bring vs to eternall life: without which walking with God, there is no hope, that we can liue with him for euer. This walking may be expreſſed in theſe 3. Firſt that there be a good and holy life. For <hi>Qualis vita, finis ita:</hi> ſuch as is the life, ſuch will be the death. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, a good fame, for that fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the bones.<note place="margin">Pro. 15</note> Thirdly, that there be a good Conſcience, for that is a continuall feaſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly we obſerue, that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men, muſt performe perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall duties of goodneſſe: euery man in his place and talling: as <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> teacheth, when the people came and demanded of him,<note place="margin">Luc. 3</note> What ſhall we do, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, He that hath two coates, let him part with him that hath none, and he that hath meate, let him doe likewiſe. Then the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans</hi> asked, What ſhall we do? He ſaid, Require no more, then
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:7797:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>that which is appointed to you. Then the Souldiers demanded, What ſhall we doe? he ſaid, Doe violence to no man, neither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe any man falſely, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with your wages. So that of euery man and woman of what degree or place ſoeuer they be, there is a generall and alſo a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and perſonall duety of goodneſſe required: which in ſumme is no more, but to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to the benefite of others all thoſe graces and bleſſings of body and minde where with God hath truſted them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The parties deſiring this duty come to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered in the next; place as the third pillar of my text for it is not ſaid, that, that this or that man deſires of a man: or that our friends deſire of vs, is our goodnes. But that, that is to be de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſired of a man, that is, that, that all the things of the world deſires of man, is his goodneſſe. Firſt then that which God deſireth of a man is his goodneſſe, as we ſaw
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:7797:54"/>before out of the Prophet, Saint <hi>Paule</hi> affirming the ſame,<note place="margin">Mich. 6</note> This is the will of God,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4</note> euen your ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification; and our Sauiour: Be you perfect,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> as your heauenly Father is perfect. And how is that? He makes his Sunne ariſe vpon the good and bad, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth rayne on the iuſt and vniuſt. That God lookes for this duty of goodneſſe at our hands, the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Talents makes it plaine, for be that had lapt vp his Talent in a napkin, was adiudged to bee caſt into fire that cannot bee quenched. Euery mans Talents and graces are giuen him of God, with this charge, <hi>Negotiamim do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec veniam:</hi> Occupy till I come: put my money, my graces of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and minde into the banke, that I may receiue my owne with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>The Parable of the wedding gatment ſhews the ſame, without which who appeares before God ſhal be bound hand &amp; foot, &amp; caſt into vtter darkneſſe. The vniuſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:7797:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>Steward that had waſted his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters goods, was called to a <hi>red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de rationem,</hi> a ſtrickt <hi>Audit</hi> for all. And ſo ſhall all wee be, for the goods and graces God hath put in our ſtewardſhips: it ſhall not auaile vs to pleade that of the Goſpell in barre: When ſaw we thee in priſon and did not viſite thee?<note place="margin">Math. 25</note> or hungry and did not feed thee? or naked and did not cloath thee? For it ſhall bee anſwered, In as much as you did it not to the leaſt of theſe, you did it not to me: depart from mee yee cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into euerlaſting fire, prepared for the Diuell and his Angels.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why God deſires this goodneſſe, is, for that in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing come wee ſo neare the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and originall goodneſſe it ſelfe, which is God, as in true &amp; ſincere goodneſſe to others. Yea euen to our enemies. For as the Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78</note> though God did often deliner the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> yet did they ſtill rebell againſt him. So infinite is the goodneſſe of God,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:7797:55"/>that by no ingratitude or rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man will hee be ouercome, vntill hee bee paſt cure. Euen ſo a good man will not vpon euery ſlight occaſion withdrawe his goodneſſe, complayning of the ingratitude and indignity of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but knowes that God lookes for goodneſſe of him, euen ſuch as himſelfe ſhewes to vile, vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and rebellious ſinners. And here obſerue, that amongſt all the reſt of the parts of goodnes that God deſires at our hands, this is not the leaſt, that as it is his goodnes to be angry with ſinne, &amp; to puniſh it in whomſoeuer he findes it,<note place="margin">Heb. 12</note> and therefore chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth euery ſonne that hee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth: ſo it is the true marke of goodnes in man, to be angry with ſin, and to labour to check and kill it.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1</note> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> expreſſeth this goodnes thus: Be yee holy in all manner of conuerſation for it is written, Be ye holy, becauſe I am holy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Angels deſire
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:7797:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>this goodneſſe of vs. Hence it is, that our Sauiour ſayth.<note place="margin">Luk. 15</note> There is ioy before the Angels for one ſinner repenting. How can it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be, but that they who greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire our goodnes, ſeeing they ſo much ioy when we returne from our wickednes: how can they but deſire earneſtly our goodnes, ſeeing that by it, the reparation of that great breach which Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and his fellowes made, is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made vp? And ſo much doe they deſire our goodnes, that they are miniſtring ſpirits about vs, ſent forth for their ſakes that are heites of ſaluation:<note place="margin">Heb. 1</note> And therefore cannot but deſire that their ſeruice and miniſtery may take that effect.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, our neighbours, euen all men, deſire this goodnes of vs.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As the members of the body doe one deſire the aſſiſtance of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, elſe would the frame of the whole body in few houres ruine and fall aſunder; ſo doth euery man deſire the goodnes of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:7797:56"/>being fellow members of one body, without which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not any long time liue. If the mouth receiued not meate, the ſtomacke diſgeſted it, the liuer tranſmitted the blood to the heart, the heart ſent it abroade to the reſt of the members, and euery ioynt of the body did not his office, to the good of another; the whole body could not liue one houre. So it is in the body of the Church &amp; Policy, if al do not labour to the good of others, it will ſpeedily grow diſeaſed and dye.</p>
            <p>The poore deſire the goodnes of our wealth and countenance: the rich the goodnes of our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and paines: the King the goodnes of our loyalty and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute: the Nobles, the goodnes of our humility and ſeruice: the ſicke and diſeaſed, the goodnes of our compaſſion and comfort the deſperate, the goodnes of our counſell and care. And ſuch is this duty of goodnes, as that it
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:7797:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>is a debt, we muſt euer owe one to another.<note place="margin">Rom. 13</note> Owe nothing to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, but that you loue one another. This Motto is written on the forehead of euery man in the world: <hi>Non ſolùm nobis nati ſumus,</hi> Wee are not borne for our ſelues: and goodnes cannot be ſo faſt bound in the affections of the heart, but it will breake out, and ſtretch it ſelfe to all that haue neede of it. Therefore truely it is ſayd of that good Father:<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma magis eſt vbi amat, quàm vbi animat:</hi> The ſoule of man is more where it loues, then where it liues.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> our ſelues deſire goodnes from our ſelues, it is a ſpeciall duty wee owe to our ſelues. All that wee ſhould loue or deſire in our ſelues, is our goodnes. If wee loue any thing elſe in our ſelues, wee loue not our owne ſoules. Thou deſireſt (ſaith a Father) to haue good ſomes, good ſeruants,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> a good wife, a good houſe, good lands,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:7797:57"/>nay, good hoſe and ſhooes; and doeſt thou not deſire <hi>te bonant?</hi> to haue thy ſelfe good? What a thing is this, that thou ſhould eſt deſire to haue all other things good, and not thy ſelfe good? Surely thou doſt croſſe thy owne deſires, with thy owne deedes. For the righteous man, nay euery man liuing, deſires goodnes of himſelfe. But the righteous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires nothing elſe but goodnes. One thing haue I deſired,<note place="margin">Pſa. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp; that will I require, that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the dayes of my life, to beholde the beauty of the Lord, and to viſite his Temple. I counted all things but dung,<note place="margin">Phil. 3</note> that I might bee made conformable to Chriſt, ſaith the Apoſtle. And ſo farre is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man in loue with good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that hee glories in the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, albeit he haue no right in the thing, and ſtormes if hee be not counted a good man. But the truely wiſe man knowing <hi>Nihl ſibi bonum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen.</note> 
               <hi>ſine ſe bono:</hi> That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:7797:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>is good to a man, vnleſſe himſelfe bee alſo good, deſires a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other things, that bee may be a good man indeed. For ſo hath he the benefit of all Gods creatures; ſo are they good and comfortable to him; elſe are they but all to his greater condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>One ſaith, that the chiefe title which God in Scripture giues himſelfe, is <hi>Bonitas,</hi> Goodneſſe.<note place="margin">Dioniſ. de diui. nom. <hi>2.1</hi>
               </note> Becauſe it is the property of all good things to communicate and inlarge themſelues to others. Therfore moſt agreeable to God, who raines downe all his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits vpon vs: and that therefore all other names of God, are but expoſitions and commentaries vpon this name. So the proper name of man is Goodnes, but in an infinite lower degree; and all his other titles and ſtiles, be they neuer ſo great and awefull, are but gloſſes and commentaries vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it. And God is pleaſed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate this name with man,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:7797:58"/>that hee might learne, that as God deſires nothing in himſelfe but goodneſſe, nor nothing more to bee proclaimed of him then his goodnes: ſo man ſhould not loue any thing in himſelfe, but goodnes: nor euer thinke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe truely honoured, but when proclamation may bee made of his goodnes.</p>
            <p>This I confeſſe, is one of the greateſt goodneſſes that can bee in vs, to loue nothing in our ſelues but our goodnes. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> hauing on a time many Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers with him at a banquet, would needes haue it diſputed, what was the greateſt thing in the world. Some of them ſayde, the bill Olympus, ſome the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, ſome the Sunne, ſome the Earth: but one of them ſayd, that ſurely the heart of man muſt needes bee the greateſt: for that in a moment of time it did paſſe through the whole worlde, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, Earth, Sea and all. For <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil mirabile praeter animum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg.</note> 
               <hi>cui mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:7797:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>nihil eſt magnum;</hi> Nothing is wonderfull but the mind of man, vnto which when it is great, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſeemes great. Therefore he that hath ſo great a minde and heart, that nothing but Heauen contaynes it (and ſuch a heart hath euery childe of God,) will loue nothing in himſelfe but goodnes, that may bring him to the place where he would be. So by hauing this great thing which euery man hath, (for euery man hath a heart) and adding but to it the leaſt thing in the worlde, which is goodnes: hee ſhall haue that in himſelfe that is worth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worldes, and will make him loue nothing in himſelfe but his goodnes.</p>
            <p>Finally, goodnes is all that all the creatures of God deſires of man.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> It is the cry of all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſaith that learned Father:<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Coelum &amp; terra, &amp; quicquid in ijs eſt, vndique mihi dicunt vt te amem, Domine, nec ceſſant hoc dicere omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vt ſint inexcuſabiles:</hi> The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:7797:59"/>and earth, and all that is in them, ſpeake vnto mee O Lord, that I ſhold loue thee; nor do they at any time ceaſe to ſpeake the ſame to all men, that they might be inexcuſable. And what is this voyce of nature, but that wee ſhould haue this goodnes which proceedes from the loue of God? Hence hath the lawe ordayned, that if thy neighbours Aſſe fall into the dirch, thou ſhouldeſt lift him vp; not onely in reſpect of thy duty to thy neighbor, but alſo to the beaſt which ſtands in need of thy helpe, of thy goodneſſe. And it is alſo commanded, that thy beaſt ſhould reſt the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day: it is a goodnes thy beaſt deſires of thee. Beſides, thou muſt not mouzel themouth of the Oxe that treades out the corne: that duty of goodnes thy Oxe deſires of thee. And hence it is ſayd,<note place="margin">Pro. 12</note> that the righteous man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardes the life of his beaſt.</p>
            <p>And becauſe wee doe not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this duty of goodneſſe to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:7797:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>the creatures, therefore doe they grone and ſigh,<note place="margin">Rom. 8</note> as people vnder a cruell Tyrant, to bee deliuered from the bondag and cruelty vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which wee hold them. And I maruell in my heart, when I ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly thinke on it, wee doe not heare them ſigh and grone. For ſurely they ſpeake in their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage aloude: and if our horrible ſinnes did not ſtrangely deafe vs, wee ſhould heare them. For euen for this cauſe, that wee doe not performe this duty of goodnes to them, but doe miſerably abuſe and tyrannize them, doe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt vs: the heauen drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the earth, the ayre infecting our bodies, the earth denying her fruite, and all of them being vp in armes againſt vs, to be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of vs for want of goodneſſe to them. For neuer was there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bloody or mercileſſe Tyrant in the world, that did ſo wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tyrannize ouer his people, as wee in this Age doe tyrannize &amp; abuſe all the good creatures of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:7797:60"/>God. Now then, if thou haſt not this goodnes to beſtow all thou haſt or art, to the good of others: thou art firſt iniurious to God: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly iniurious to the Angells: Thirdly iniurious to Man-kinde: Fourthly iniurious to thy owne Soule: Fiftly iniurious to all the creatures. Moſt iniurious art thou to God, becauſe thou rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt againſt him; to the Angells; becauſe thou grieueſt them; to Man, becauſe thou doeſt not loue him: to thy ſelfe, becauſe thou hateſt thy own Soule: to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, becauſe thou abufeſt them.</p>
            <p>Seeing then, all that God and Angells, Men and thy own Soule, the heauens, and all the creatures deſire of thee, is thy goodneſſe: thou art taught hereby to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and order thy affections and deſires towards all men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame rule: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not to deſire that they might be rich, honorable, learned, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull or the like: but to deſire that they might be good, godly, pious,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:7797:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>gracious, and in all manner of conuerſation godly.</p>
            <p>And not onely ſo, but withall, that they may grow in goodnes; for that alſo doth God, Angels, men, our ſelues, and the creatures deſire of vs. <hi>Solus Deus melior eſſe non vult, quia non valet,</hi> ſaith that deuout Father: Onely God it is that will not be better,<note place="margin">Ber.</note> becauſe he cannot be better; but with men, it muſt not be ſo. <hi>Minime pro certo bonus es, ſi non vis eſſe meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, vbi incipis nolle eſſe melior, ibi deſinis eſſe bonus.</hi> For a truth thou art not good, if thou deſireſt not to be better: For where thou beginneſt not to deſire to be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there thou leaueſt off to bee good at all. Therfore we muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may grow fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith to ſaith, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace to grace,<note place="margin">Eph. 4</note> follow the truth in loue, &amp; grow vp into him in all things, who is the head, which is Chriſt. Euen as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from a ſmall beginning, grows till it come to a ful ſtature and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of euery part: ſo muſt chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:7797:61"/>grow.<note place="margin">Phil. 3</note> This was the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of all holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I follow hard towards the marke for the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus. Steppe after ſteppe did this holy man follow, till he came to the very top of holines.</p>
            <p>Thus are wee come to the fourth and laſt columne of this building, <hi>viz:</hi> the reaſons enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing this duty of goodnes. Theſe I finde in the Text to be ſix. The Firſt I called <hi>Facilitas officij,</hi> the facility of the duty. For it is but one duty for all, onely goodneſſe. It was wont to be ſaid, <hi>Tria ſunt omnia:</hi> Three things includes all things: But now it is ſaid, <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeſt omnia,</hi> one thing is all things. Goodneſſe anſweres to all. At the firſt God gaue man 10. commandements, but becauſe the number ſeemed tedious, our Sauiour contracted them all into two, the loue of God, and of our neighbours. But here for our better helpe and memory, all are reduced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one, namely, <hi>Bonitas,</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:7797:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>Goodneſſe. <hi>Vnum neceſſarium:</hi> one thing is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>And yet being but one, I know not how it grows heauie; but ſure I am, that as our Sauior ſaid, to that good young man, that had performed all the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from his youth vp; yet one thing is wanting: ſo he may true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay to vs all, This one thing of goodneſſe is awanting. What ſhame is it to neglect one duety, ſo eaſy, becauſe but one duety &amp; no more? What ſhame not to do a duety ſo eaſy as is goodnes? the very name of it makes it eaſy: For we loue the name. And <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia difficilia facit amor facilia:</hi> Loue makes all difficult things, to be of great facility. What is more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, then to vnderſtand and doe that which is good? Is it not more eaſy then to doe euill? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there is much more difficulty in doing euill then in doing good. For as nothing is more difficult then for birds to make wings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtorme, ſloops to ſayle
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:7797:62"/>againſt the winde and tide, Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets to moue againſt the motion and courſe of the firmament; ſo is nothing more difficult for man then to fly againſt the blaſt of the Holy Ghoſt, to make head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the floods and ſtormes of his owne Conſcience, and to run againſt the firmament of Gods commandements: all which doe mainely reſiſt the euill actions of ſinfull men, and aſſiſt the inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors of Gods children. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was ſaid to <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 9</note> It is hard for thee to kicke againſt the pricks. Hence the wicked them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues confeſſe, that they are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the way of wickedneſſe: but the godly finde no ſuch laſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and wearineſſe in the way of godlineſſe; but doe with <hi>Dauid,</hi> runne the way of Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, nay, they take more pleaſure in them, then in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of riches; they are the very ioy of their hearts. Therefore if goodneſſe bee not eaſy vnto vs, we are not yet in Chriſt; for vnto
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:7797:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>his, the commandements are not grieuous, His yoake is eaſy. And albeit the Philoſopher ſaith, that the obiect of vertue, is <hi>Bonum &amp; difficile,</hi> a good, difficult and hard to compaſſe:<note place="margin">Sen.</note> And the wiſe Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: that <hi>Res difficilis est Virtus:</hi> Vertue is a difficult point to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: yet that is onely: Firſt in reſpect of the naturall man,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1</note> who perceiues not the things of the ſpirit of God, and therefore hath great reluctation in doing of good. Secondly, in that euill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it ſelf vnto him, in the habit of good, and ſo makes the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the act more facill. Thirdly, in reſpect of the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that Sathan makes by his manifold temptations, making way for the commiſſion of ſinne, caſting blocks in the way of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. But ſimply in reſpect of the nature of the thing it ſelfe, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vertue is much more facill to a man endued with the ſpirit of God, then wickedneſſe and vice. And therefore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:7797:63"/>ſaid, I can doe all things through him that comforts me.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon I ſaid,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> was <hi>Neceſsitas officij,</hi> the neceſſity of the duty, taken from the bond, whereby we are tyed to God, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, men, our ſelues, and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: to all which, but chiefely to God, we are by ſo many obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations bound to performe this duty. All theſe doe cry vnto vs; <hi>Bonum te fecit Deus, &amp; tu faceres bonitatem:</hi> God did therfore make thee good, that thou ſhouldeſt do that is good. Therfore if we haue not this goodneſſe, theſe foure, God, Angels, man, and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſhall riſe vp in iudgement againſt vs. Miſerable men that we are, who ſhall haue, <hi>Deum ira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Conſcientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mordentem, ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos inim cos, &amp; creaturas armatas:</hi> God angry with vs, our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence biting and gnawing vs, our friends turned to be our enemies, and the creatures armed againſt vs, and condemne vs for want of this goodneſſe which they deſire
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:7797:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>of vs, and we are tied to performe to them all. The wife doe ſay,<note place="margin">Sen.</note> that the Lawes appoint no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt ingrate and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull men, but in reſpect of immanity and greatneſſe of the offence, leaues it vnto God to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh; whereas they diſcerne and appoint puniſhments for theeues, murtherers, and other malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. Let vs then take heede of Gods moſt ſeuere iudgements for our monſtrous ingratitude, who being bound vnto him ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely for his vnſpeakeable goodneſſe, haue in vs ſo little goodneſſe, as that neyther God, Angels, Man, our ſelues, nor the creatures, can haue any good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of vs, but all vnthankefull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>But if the neceſſity might not moue vs, yet, <hi>Modus officij,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the manner of the duty, which is the third reaſon, may worke with vs. It is greatly deſired, ſought for, nay beſought and intreated at our hands; whereas God might
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:7797:64"/>haue commanded it. To deny a duty to him, who louingly deſires and intreates the diſcharge of it, and that without our hurt, nay to our eternall good: (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeakes, who deſired a fruite that might further the <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians</hi> reckoning:<note place="margin">Phil. 4</note> not a gift for himſelfe, but a fruite of the ſpirit, euen goodneſſe, that odour that ſmells ſweete, a Sacrifice accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table &amp; pleaſing to God:) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I ſay, a due debt ſo ſweetely intreated, ſo profitable to them that pay it, as that it inricheth them more and more, and the oftener they pay it, the more they haue, being like the treaſures of Gods houſe, the more wee taſt them, the more in-exhauſted they are; to deny this debt ſo ſweetely demanded, ſo profitable being performed, is great inhumanity, and no leſſe indiſcretion.</p>
            <p>Yet if the manner of deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding do not moue vs,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> let <hi>Tempus officij,</hi> the time of performing this duty which is the fourth motiue,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:7797:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Holy Ghoſt vſeth, ſtirre vp this goodneſſe in vs. He doth not ſay, that which ſhall bee, or hath beene deſired, but that which is euen now deſired; whileſt the beames of Gods goodneſſe by the preaching of the Goſpel, and other infinite bleſſings beſtowed on vs, doe ſhine vpon vs. Euen now let vs ſhew forth this fruite of the ſpirit, this goodnes, whilſt we haue time, let vs doe good.<note place="margin">Gal. 6</note> Let vs remember our creator in the dayes of our youth,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12</note> before the dayes come, in which we will ſay, we haue no pleaſure in them. Let vs euer be doing ſome good. <hi>Non ſemper aeſtas fuerit, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ponite nidos,</hi> the ſommer will not laſt euer, let vs make our neſts againſt the ſharpe aſſaults of winter. The day will not continue for euer, the night comes when no man can worke. Our time is but ſhort and vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; one little <hi>nunc,</hi> one ſhort now; therefore wholly to bee ſpent in goodneſſe. To do good and diſtribute forget not, for
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:7797:65"/>with ſuch Satrifice God is, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. If we conſider in what miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable plight the fooliſh virgins are that tooke not their time,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> or the rich glutton that abuſed his time,<note place="margin">Luc. 16.</note> we will make more pretious account of time then we do.</p>
            <p>And becauſe, there is none of Gods bleſſings greater then time, and yet none more abuſed, I muſt not be ſlack in commending this argument of time vnto you ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing largely. For all of vs ſpend our times too careleſly, eyther <hi>malè agendo,</hi> or <hi>nihil agendo,</hi> or <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud agendo;</hi> in doing wickedly, in doing nothing, or in doing euery thing rather then that we ſhould do. Conſider therefore, I pray you, aduiſedly theſe few argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to ſtirre vs vp to the right vſe of our time.</p>
            <p>Conſider firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the diligence of the Holy Ghoſt al ouer the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in admoniſhing vs to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrue and make much of time,<note place="margin">Syr. 4</note> and eſchew the thing that is euill. Giue not thy yeares to the cruell:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5</note>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:7797:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is a very fooliſh and mad thing to giue ſo pretious a thing as is our time, to ſo cruell an enemy as is Sathan, ſpending it in his ſeruice. Redeeme the time:<note place="margin">Ephe. 5</note> that is, purchaſe it backe againe out of morgage, at any rate. Whileſt wee haue time, let vs doe good.<note place="margin">Gal. 6</note> Infinite are the paſſages of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where the holy Ghoſt inſiſts purpoſely vpon this argument of preſeruing our time: the day of the Lord will come as a theefe in the night, as ſorrow vpon a woman in trauell, as the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of the Eaſt into the Weſt: Therefore watch, ſaith our Sauiour, make vſe of this preſent time.</p>
            <p>Conſider withall,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the creatures, who all of them obſerue their times. For hauing receiued a time to worke in, they doe all their buſineſſe they can doe in that time, and ſuffer not the time to ſpend in vaine. Therefore the Preacher tells vs, <hi>Omnia tempus habent,</hi>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:7797:66"/>There is a time for euery thing vnder the Sunne.</p>
            <p>Conſider alſo,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the nature of time it ſelfe.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For 1. it is ſhort: our dayes are ſhort and full of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery;<note place="margin">Iob 14</note> they are but a ſpanne long, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith: a thouſand yeers with the Lord, are but as yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day that is paſt.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. They are ſwift,<note place="margin">Iob 7 <hi>Sens</hi>
               </note> euen as a weauers ſhuttle. <hi>Infinita eſt velocitas temporis, pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt quod viuimus, &amp; puncto mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi> ſaith the wiſe <hi>Romane,</hi> Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite is the ſwiftneſſe of our time, it is but a point or moment that wee liue, and leſſe then a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. It is irrecouerable, as wordes ſpoken cannot bee recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, no more can time that is ſpent be reuoked, if a man would giue a world for it. Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſhort, ſo ſwift, ſo irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerable, it would be well ſpent.</p>
            <p>Let vs then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of time:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> that deuout Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laments the loſſe of it thus:<note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>Heu tempore nihil pretioſius, at ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die nihil vilius inuenitur;</hi> Alas, there
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:7797:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>is nothing more pretious then time, and yet at this day, there is not found a thing that men make viler account of: The pretiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time is ſet forth vntows, in theſe three conceptions. Firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> in that the poſſeſſion of time is very rare, ſeeing there is but ſtill one time onely, and that is the preſent time. But for the time paſt, and time to come, neither of them are in our poſſeſſion. As it is ſayde of the Phoenix, that there is neuer but one of them in the world: ſo it may bee ſayd of time. Therefore ſeeing all rare things are pretious and deare, how much more ſhould time bee deare and pretious vnto vs, being ſo rare, that there is neuer but one time, and that ſo ſhort as is a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? 2. There is a place,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in which one houre of time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in, would bee more worth then a world, and that place is Hell; where the damned ſpirits would giue a thouſand worldes for one houre to repent in, if they
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:7797:67"/>had them: but can neuer obtaine it.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. In oue houre of time, oue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man may ſo behaue himſelfe, by the helpe of Gods ſpirit, and vſe of holy meanes, that he may pleaſe God, obtaine remiſſion of his ſinnes, the grace of God in Chriſt, and eternall ſaluation. Therefore time being ſo pretious and vnualuable, would bee ſpent in goodnes.</p>
            <p>Conſider beſides,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that we are debters of all &amp; euery part of our time: and none of it is our own, nor doe wee owe it to one, but to many. And how fooliſh, or rather madde were hee, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing but a little ſtocke, and ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it all to ſundry creditors, more to the leaſt then all his ſtocke comes vnto, would be ſo prodigall and graceleſſe as to caſt it all at one chance of the Dice? Would you not account ſuch a man worthy of Bedlem, and to be bound and beaten ſoundly till hee came to his right ſences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? Surely ſuch is the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:7797:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>of euery one of vs: our ſtock of time, is wonderful ſhort: for euen now wee are, and euen now wee are not: yet doe wee ſpend it, as if wee ſhould neuer come to the bottom of our ſtore.<note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>O,</hi> ſaith that good Father, <hi>Sicog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouiſſes quam multa, &amp; quam multis debeas, videres quod nihil eſt, quod facis:</hi> If thou did deft but know how much &amp; to how many thou oweft thy time, thou wouldeſt confeſſe, that all thou doeſt is iuſt nothing. 1.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thou oweſt to Chriſt Ieſus all thy life, for hee layde downe his life for thine. 2.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thy ſins paſt require thy life to come, to bring foorth fruites worthy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement of life: <hi>Recogitare om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes annos tuos, in amarioudine ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae tuae:</hi> To thinke vpon all thy yeares paſt, in the bitterneſſe of thy ſoule. 3.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The deſire of that glory, which eye hath not ſeene, care heard, nor entred into mans heart, is another creditour to which thou oweſt all thy time: And wilt thou not giue thy ſelfe,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:7797:68"/>and all that thou haſt for this? And yet when all is done, the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of this life are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of the glory that ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. To the laſt creditour, which is God himſelfe, thou ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt all thou haſt, yea euery mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy life and time. For he it was that made thee, bleſſed thee, miniſtred all good things to thee; and craues the well v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of thy time, that hee might for euer glorifie thee.</p>
            <p>If wee conſider the account that muſt bee made of our time,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> it will moue vs much to beſtowe it well. It will bee a moſt ſtrickt one.<note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>Omne tempus tibi impenſum, requiretur àte, qualiter ſit expenſum:</hi> Euery houre of time that God hath beſtowed on thee in this life, ſhall bee required of thee, in what ſort it is ſpent. And it is moſt ſure, that <hi>Sicut capillus</hi> (as the ſame Father ſaith) <hi>non peribit de capite, ſic nec momentum de tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore:</hi> As one haire of the head ſhall not periſh, ſo one moment
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:7797:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>of time ſhall not paſſe without being accounted for. O how ſtrong and vnanſwerable an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument will the benefit of time be againſt them that haue abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it! and wholly beſtowed it to the diſhonour of God, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying of their owne luſts!</p>
            <p>But ſeeing moſt men make no reckoning of this account; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> let it be conſidered, that time, in a moſt ſtrange and ſpeciall manner is in our poſſeſſion. For of all the things of this world, onely time is our owne, and nothing elſe. For as that wiſe Heathen ſayde well: <hi>Reliqua à nobis aliena ſunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen.</note> 
               <hi>tempus tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtrum eſt,</hi> All other things may be taken from vs, but time is ſuch a thing as no Tyrant can take from vs. Time doth ſo adhere to our beings, that if wee loſe time, wee doe in ſome ſort loſe our ſelues. So that hee who loſeth the one halfe of his time, loſeth halfe himſelfe; hee that loſeth all his time, loſeth all himſelfe; and looke how much
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:7797:69"/>a man loſeth of his time, ſo much hee loſeth of himſelfe. Therefore in this conſideration, euery man being moſt deare vnto himſelfe, wee ſhould haue great care of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our time wel, that we do not vtterly loſe our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Yet happely none of theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons being able to worke out any reſpect for times priuiledge,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> let it not be forgotten, that the loſſe of time is a certain kind of death. For it is the loſſe of life, and what is that I pray you, but death? Yet alas, who is it that ſettes any deare rate vpon the time? Who it it that inhaunceth the price of it?<note place="margin">Sen.</note> 
               <hi>Quis intelligit,</hi> ſaith the learned <hi>Romane, ſe quotidiè mori?</hi> Who is it that vnderſtands how he doth daily die? <hi>Quotidiè morimur, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidiè demitur aliqua pars vitae, et tunc cùm creſcimus, vita decreſcit.</hi> We die daily, daily ſome part of our life is taken from vs, and whileſt wee increaſe and grow, our life doth decreaſe and fade. The houre glaſſe which wee hourely behold,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:7797:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>and doth now meaſure out my ſpeech vnto you, is a perfect em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme, and reſemblance of the loſſe of our liues, by the hand of time: for as it doth inſenſibly growe great below, ſo doth it waſte and growe leſſe and leſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, vntill it bee vtterly ſpent. Such is the ſpending and loſſe of mans life by time: euery moment depriues him of a little portion of life, and neuer leaues till it haue depriued him of all, and left him timeleſſe as the glaſſe is ſandleſſe. Theſe conſiderations, would God might worke in vs ſome care to beſtow our times better then we haue done, in piety and goodnes which my text deſires now of vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7797:70"/>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:7797:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SECOND Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PRO. 19.22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>That that is deſired of a man is his goodneſſe, <hi>or,</hi> the deſire of a man is his kindneſſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S you haue beene graciouſly pleaſed to take a view of the front and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roomes in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of goodneſſe, ſo lend mee your patience, I beſeech you, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while, till by this Perſpectiue, I giue you a ful ſuruey of the whole building.</p>
            <p>The next roome then that you ſee, affordes another argument out of the Text to enforce this duty of goodneſſe: which I
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:7797:71"/>call <hi>Familiaritas officij,</hi> The famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity and naturallneſſe of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: being ſuch, as that no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute but hath a particular good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and all for our good, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which wee could not liue an houre. Therefore one ſaith, that <hi>Bonitas eſt id,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Raymund.</note> 
               <hi>ratione cuius bonum agit bonum:</hi> Goodneſſe is that, by reaſon whereof, good doth that which is good. The creature is therefore naturally good, that it might doe vs ſome good; if then wee would enioy the goodnes of the creatures, and not turne thoſe excellent bleſſings into curſings, let vs imitate them in goodneſſe, ſeeing wee are Lords of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. They haue all their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the benefite of vs, and one of another: Let vs not bee more dull then the inſenſible creatures. There is written vpon euery creature theſe three ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; <hi>Accipe beneficium, redde debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, caue ſupplicium:</hi> Receiue the benefite of the creatures: doe the duty of the creatures: take heed
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:7797:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the puniſhment for abuſing &amp; not imitating the creatures. If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou wilt take the comforts of the creatures, and not doe the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the creatures, bee ſure thou ſhalt not auoide the puniſhment: the benefit of them is, the ſupply of thy wants: the duty is good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and thankefulnes to God for that ſupply;<note place="margin">Deut. 28.28</note> the puniſhment madneſſe, for want of that duty.</p>
            <p>The laſt but not the leaſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prouoke this duty of goodneſſe, I call <hi>Excellentia officij,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The excellency of the duty: that, euen that excellent duty of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; none elſe. The Pronoune <hi>quòd,</hi> is the force of this reaſon: as if hee ſhould haue ſayde, That duty and none elſe: that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly and alone, and none elſe but that. Not wiſedome, nor know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor honour, nor riches, nor ſtrength, nor beauty, not any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing but that, euen that goodnes which anſweres to all. Truely may that bee ſpoken of goodnes, which the wiſe King
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:7797:72"/>ſpake of that excellent woman;<note place="margin">Pro. 31</note> many daughters haue done vertu ouſly, but thou ſurmounteſt them all. Many graces are commended, but goodnes ſurpaſſeth them all. There was neuer any ſhippe brought home any ſuch marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe; neuer any vineyard bore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch grapes: neuer field any ſuch fruit; neuer wooll, any ſuch cloath; neuer flaxe, any ſuch lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen. For ſtrength and honor are the cloathing of goodnes, and in the latter day, goodnes ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce. To goodnes it ſhall bee ſayd,<note place="margin">Mat. 25</note> Beholde good and faithfull ſeruant, thou haſt beene faithfull in little, I will make thee ruler o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer much, enter into thy Maſters ioy.</p>
            <p>Now the holy Ghoſt not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great cauſe hath thus fortified &amp; enforced this duty of goodnes with ſo many ſtrong motiues and reaſons. Becauſe Sathan im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnes nothing more then the progreſſe and ſucceſſe of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For 1. whereas the holy
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:7797:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ghoſt commends the duety to vs, from the facilitie of it, and that in a double reſpect: Firſt, becauſe but one duty: Secondly, for that a louely duty, the duty of goodnes: Sathan labours to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe this argument by inſtilling this perſwaſion intows, that a good mans life is like a ring: the beginning &amp; ending, is without beginning and ending: like a husbandmans life, euer plowing, or harrowing, or ſowing, or dunging, or weeding, or reaping, ſtill in labour: from prayer to ſermons: from ſermons to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and meditation, from that to reading and diſcourſing, from one holy exerciſe to another. Therefore not ſo eaſie a matter, ſaith hee, as they would make it ſeeme. And beſides, neither is it ſo louely a duty, ſaith he, for few of any fort can away with the company of goodnes. Thus ſpake he in the Scribes and Phariſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Sauiour Chriſt: Doe any of the Rulers beleeue in him?
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:7797:73"/>2.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Whereas it is recommended by the neceſſity of it, hee labours to take off that argument, as hee did in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Who is the Lord that I ſhould obey him? As in thoſe wicked: Who is the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty that wee ſhould ſerue him?<note place="margin">Iob 21</note> and what profit ſhould we haue,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> if wee pray vnto him? 3. Whereas the duty of goodnes is commended, in that it is deſired and entreated of vs, hee perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and ſuggeſteth that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, piety, religion, and holineſſe, are but matters of forme and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie; elſe they would bee more ſtrictly commanded, and the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect more ſeuerely puniſhed.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Whereas the argument of the preſent time enforceth the duty; hee perſwadeth, (as wee may ſee him ſpeake out of the mouth of the vngodly crue in the olde worlde, &amp; as hee ſpeakes in the liues generally of all ſorts of men in this euill world:)<note place="margin">Sap. 2</note> Our time is ſhort, come let vs enioy the good things that are preſent: let vs vſe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:7797:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>the creatures as in youth, let vs fill our ſelues with new wine, let vs annoint our ſelues with the beſt oyntments, let not the floure of our time paſſe away, let vs crown our ſelues with roſe buds; let none of vs go without his part of voluptuouſneſſe, let vs leaue ſome token of our pleaſures eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, for this is our portion, this our lot. This perſwaſion he vſed with the rich man in the Goſpell, whoſe ſentence was, <hi>Hâc nocte repetent animam tuam,</hi> This night will they fetch away thy Soule, and then whoſe ſhall all theſe things be?</p>
            <p>Fiftly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> whereas it is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder the reaſon of natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he labours to perſwade that it is moſt vnnaturall, as the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſpeake in the Pſalm: Whileſt men doe good to themſelues, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man will ſpeake good of them; but not whileſt they doe good to others, and our ſelues are the neareſt to our ſelues. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in nature we ſhould haue all
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:7797:74"/>care of our ſelues. Laſtly where it is commended vnder the title of excellency, Satan perſwades that the moſt excellent things are, honours, riches, carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, fleſhly delights, eaſe, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the like: euen as <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> did with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the golden Calues: Theſe are thy Gods O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that brought thee out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> and as he did to our Sauiour, ſhewing him all the kingdomes of the world, as the moſt excellent things, and to be preferred before all goodneſſe, all duties to God or man. Therefore our good God knowing that Sathan by might and maine oppoſeth the growth and thrift of goodneſſe, doth here thus ſtrongly enforce it, by a ſixe fold cable: of reaſon.</p>
            <p>But alas, for all this, ſo little do all theſe motiues preuaile, and ſo much doth Sathan, that it may be ſaid of the greateſt part of men in our times as truely, as one ſpake truely and merrily of the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:7797:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>Pope; that all his holineſſe was in his heeles, and for that cauſe men deſired ſo much to kiſſe his foote: ſo all our goodneſſe is (at the beſt) in our lips, but for the moſt part in our heeles, and on our backs; &amp; therfore we make ſo many kiſſes and applauſes, and ſeruices on our heeles and backs; many meane men (God knowes) carying as much coſt about their heeles, as our beſt noble men within this forty yeeres wore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their heads. And this is the greateſt part of our times good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>But now that I am ſpeaking of the excellency of this duety, I ſhould doe you wrong to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale any part of her beauty from you. Acquaint your ſelues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I pray you with theſe three conſiderations, to the end you may the better be acquainted with the excellency of goodneſſe. The firſt is, what kinds of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe there are. The Second, what rules of goodneſſe are to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:7797:75"/>The third, what are the euidences and markes of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>I finde but three kindes.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, preſeruing goodneſſe. We muſt not doe good to our ſelues onely, but to all others, in labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to keepe and preſerue them from the contagion of ſinne: from falling from grace and their moſt holy calling and profeſſion; and that by all meanes, as well exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of life, as ſpeeches ſeaſoned with ſalt. For it is the mayne ſcope of mans life in this world to draw others to ſaluation. So did <hi>Barnabas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 11</note> who comming to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> and ſeeing the grace of God that was giuen them, confirmed them therein, exhorting that with purpoſe of heart they would cleaue to the Lord.</p>
            <p>The Second is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vniting good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to ſet men at vnity, who are at variance.<note place="margin">Math. 5</note> Hence Chriſt calls peace-makers the children of God. For no ſonne reſembles his father ſo much in any quality
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:7797:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>as thoſe reſemble God, that make peace.<note place="margin">Pſal. 67</note> For God makes men to be of one mind in a houſe, and ſo will the children of God alſo labour to do.</p>
            <p>There is another kinde of goodneſſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> called communicating goodneſſe: and this hath foure ſteppes or degrees. For firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> we muſt communicate temporall things vnto the neceſſity of the Saints.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> And for ſpirituall things and bleſſings,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4</note> as euery man hath receiued, ſo muſt he diſtribute.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we muſt bee plentifull in the workes of mercy: not in being good to ſome, and not to others: but in being rich in good workes to all. Charge them to bee rich in good workes.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6</note> Herein we muſt be like <hi>Dorcas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 9</note> who cloathed the poore with garments ſhee made at her owne coſt. Like the good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who opens the palme of her hand to the poore:<note place="margin">Pro. 31</note> like good <hi>Iob</hi> whom the loynes of the poore bleſſed. Thirdly,<note place="margin">Iob. 31</note> wee muſt bee
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:7797:76"/>much in goodneſſe: which is in communicating to others aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly the bleſſings wherewith God hath ſtored vs, not in louing onely, but in liberall ſupplying their wants alſo. As <hi>Obadiah</hi> did in ſpending his liuing and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring his life,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 12</note> to hide a thouſand of the Lords Prophets from the rage of wicked <hi>Iezabell.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, we muſt bee ſuper-abundant in goodneſſe, like the poore wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, that would rather want her ſelfe,<note place="margin">Luc. 21</note> then be wanting in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution of the Lords treaſury; and therefore caſt into the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban two mites, euen all ſhe had. So that we muſt relieue the wants of others as wee are able, and ſometimes aboue that we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as <hi>Paule</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that to their power and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their power,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 8</note> they were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to miniſter to the neceſſities of the brethren.</p>
            <p>Now are we to know what are the rules to be obſerued in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thoſe I finde to bee 4.
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:7797:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>The firſt rule is, that we muſt doe good onely of that is our owne. No robbing of <hi>Peter</hi> to pay <hi>Paule.</hi> No dealing vniuſtly with any to doe good to others:<note place="margin">Iſ. 61</note> ſuch Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice God abhorres. Hence <hi>Dauid</hi> would not offer burnt Sacrifice of that which coſt him nothing,<note place="margin">1. Cron. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which was not his own. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we muſt doe good with ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity and cheerefulneſſe:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for God loues a cheerefull giuer.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 9</note> Therfore one ſaith very aptly, Well doing muſt proceed from well wiſhing,<note place="margin">Ambr.</note> for ſuch as is the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch wil be the action. Therefore we muſt giue freely, elſe it is no gift. In do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good we muſt not bee huck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, wee muſt not truck one for another, for euen Publicans and ſinners doe the ſame. Therefore one ſaith truely, <hi>Danda ſunt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia, non foeneranda:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lact.</note> Good turnes and benefites are freely to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, not couetouſly put to vſury. Thirdly, the next rule is, that we ſo giue to others, that we diſable not our ſelues, from iuſt mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:7797:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>of our ſelues.<note place="margin">Act. 11</note> All ſent ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour to the brethren, but yet it was according to their ability: but herein I neede not ſpend much argument, for our age giues not a man of this exceſſe. The laſt rule is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> that wee muſt doe all the good wee can, within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of our calling; and not ſo onely, but alſo hinder all the euill wee can hinder by any meanes.</p>
            <p>But here ſome may obiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, God himſelfe doth not all the good hee may doe, nor yet hinder all the euill he may; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neyther are we bound to do it.</p>
            <p>For ſatisfaction hereof,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I ſay, that in this behalfe we are not to imitate God. Firſt, becauſe wee are ſubiect to that Law, Thou ſhalt not doe euill,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> that good may come thereof: but God is not ſubiect to any Law, no, not to his owne Law: beſides, hee hath power to diſpence with it; ſo haue not wee. Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> hee
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:7797:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>is able to draw good out of euill, and light out of darkenes, which we cannot doe. Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> God is the generall good; wee are the particular good. Now, betwixt theſe two there is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. For the particular good muſt procure all the good, and hinder all the euill it can, within his calling: but to the nature of the vniuerſall good, there are theſe three things appertayning. Firſt, that all things bee good in ſome meaſure of goodneſſe.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that ſome things be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then others. Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that thoſe things which are defectiue in goodneſſe, that is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> all euill things, ſhould be ordayned to the common good. As for better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation: In a well ordered houſe; firſt, all the parts thereof are good in their kind. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſome are better then others, and of more maieſty and vſe: veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of honor &amp; diſhonor.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thoſe parts of the houſe that are deſtitute of goodneſſe, as
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:7797:78"/>ſinkes, draughts, and ſuch voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding places, (ſeruing for baſe, yet neceſſary vſes) are ordayned to the common good of the whole houſe, and ſo, as that it cannot want them, without a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience. And therefore if the maſter builder (to preuent theſe particular euills) ſhould leaue them our of his building, he ſhould preiudice and hurt the common good of his houſe, which cannot bee without them. So hath our God prouided in this goodly building of the World, that euery man ſhould bee good in his nature and kinde: and that ſome ſhould be veſſels of honor, better then the reſt, and withall that the wicked and impenitent, which are the ſinks and draughts to keepe the reſt of the houſe ſweete, ſhould for the common good, exerciſe, and ſeruice of the whole houſe, be tollerated as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, though ſtinking and noy-ſome euills.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
            </p>
            <p>Next are wee to conſider the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:7797:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>markes and euidences of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; that it may bee knowne of euery man. It is ſo painted out in the holy Scriptures, and in ſuch broade characters, that euen run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners may reade them. Therefore if you would know where good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is by the head, you muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe foure enrollements, Firſt, her witneſſes. Secondly, her ſeales and aſſurances. Thirdly, vſhers. Fourthly, her atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the witneſſes which te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie for goodneſſe, are to bee found out. For if witneſſes bee needefull in euery doubtfull caſe, then to prooue where true good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is, witneſſes will bee moſt needefull. If you pleaſe to call for them,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.</note> Saint <hi>Paùle</hi> hath rankt them for you into a ſhort but ſweete ſumme. Theſe witneſſes are without all exception; they wil proue infallibly where good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is. Let vs produce them. The firſt witneſſe, is a care to come out of our ſinnes. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:7797:79"/>is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> a clearing of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, by a true and vnfayned repentance.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt ſinne, and our ſelues for our ſinnes.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth is, a holy feare to fall into any ſin againe.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fift is, a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be out of that fearefull and damnable eſtate.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixt is a zeale of Gods glory.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth is a puniſhing and taking vengeance of our ſelues for our ſinnes, that God may not puniſh vs nor take vengeance on vs, here or hereafter. Examine the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy heart by theſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: If theſe witneſſe for thee, then happy art thou that euer thou waſt borne: if not, labour to get theſe witneſſes; but take heede of ſuborning them.</p>
            <p>The ſeales and aſſurances of goodneſſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> come next to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined. Call for them of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1</note> they are alſo ſeauen in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. The firſt of them is a liuely faith working by loue.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> a ſound knowledge of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:7797:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>God in Ieſus Chriſt. The third is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> temperance in all the good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the fourth is pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to beare ſweetely whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer God ſhall pleaſe to lay vpon him. The fift is godlineſſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> not to ſtagger or ſwerue from the commandements of God for any diſaſter. The ſixt is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> brotherly kindneſſe in diſpenſing the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God. The laſt is,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> loue of God and man, euen our enemies, that they may not want the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of our helpe in body, goods, and minde. If theſe things be amongſt vs, and abound, wee ſhall neuer bee vnfruitfull in the knowledge of our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> Theſe ſeales make our calling and election ſure, for if theſe things be in vs, we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fall. Let our labour bee to get theſe ſeales of goodneſſe, to ſeale vnto vs the inheritance of Heauen.</p>
            <p>But the better to know this noble Empreſſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> this goodneſſe, we muſt alſo behold her vſhers.
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:7797:80"/>For as Kings and noble Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are knowne by their vſhers, euen ſo is goodnes. Now ſhee hath not only one, but fiue ſeueral vſhers;<note place="margin">Gal. 5</note> no quarter waiters, they waite all at once.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led loue, for all true goodneſſe proceeds from loue.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is ioy, for goodnes reioyceth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it doth any good. The third is peace,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for euen the peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding, is in the heart of him that loues goodnes.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth is long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, for no iniuries can abate his goodnes.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The laſt is gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to entertaine ſweetly all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of doing good. And then followes goodnes. All theſe I call vſhers to goodnes, becauſe they leade and conduct goodnes to all her honourable actions: for theſe make the way for good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to worke.</p>
            <p>In a word,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the laſt meanes to know goodnes by, is her atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants. They are not many, but they are very excellent: you may
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:7797:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>euer know her by them. They are but three:<note place="margin">Gal. 5</note> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> accounts them; but they are worth all the glittering traynes of Kings and Emperours of the world.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> One of them is called Faith, a fit atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant to waite on goodnes and all great perſonages.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is Meekneſſe, the ſonne and heire of Faith, euermore at the heeles of goodnes, that ſhee ſwell not with any conceite of her owne worth. The laſt is Temperance,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> another of Faiths iſſue, to bring goodnes onely neceſſaries, and to keepe off all ſuperfluities.</p>
            <p>Thus goes goodnes attended, you eaſily may know her by her traine, no King in the worlde is ſo nobly attended. For ſeldome doe ſuch ſeruants as theſe get any roome to ſerue in with great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages. Onely goodnes giues them entertaynement, elſe they might goe a begging. For who will admit into his ſeruice, ſuch poore, baſe, bare, leane, hunger-bitten ſtrangers, as faith, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:7797:81"/>and temperance; but I muſt make an end. Thus you ſee what a worlde of excellent matter my theame offers mee: euen a whole body of Diuinity, an Ocean of learning. But I muſt now be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to haue brought you thus farre acquainted with goodneſſe: in hope that Gods grace may ſo work the loue of it in your harts, that you may be enamoured and rauiſhed with the wonderfull beautie of it.</p>
            <p>And that this beautifull <hi>Rahel</hi> may poſſeſſe the loue of your hearts, the onely way is, to put away that bleare eyde <hi>Leah,</hi> the loue of the world; for the loue of goodneſſe, and the loue of this world can neuer ſtand in any league together. The ſicke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon though hee change his bedde and lodging neuer ſo oft, hath neuer the better reſt, becauſe hee carries his ſickneſſe with him, the cauſe of his vnreſt. So though we lie neuer ſo ſoft, though we think neuer ſo well of our ſelues, yea
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:7797:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>except wee put away the loue of our goods, which doth hinder e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore the loue of goodnes, we ſhall neuer become the children of goodneſſe, or heires with God.</p>
            <p>Temporall things, may wel be compared to the tree that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephant leanes vnto, that beeing halfe cut thorow, deceiues him when he leanes vnto it. Like vnto mandrage, which if duly taken, is good phificke, but if immoderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it caſts one aſleepe, congeales the ſpirits, and killes the naturall faculties: So doe riches and the things of this life, if we loue them immoderately; they caſt vs into ſtrange dreames, make vs growe colde in deuotion and religion, congeales our affections, and in concluſion kils both ſoule &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Like the ſeedes of henbane, which kill all birds ſauing Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes,<note place="margin">Auicenna.</note> to whom they are nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing food: &amp; it kils not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as one ſaith, becauſe their veines are ſo narrow, that the fumes of it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:7797:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>paſſe to the heart, to kill it, as they doe to other creatures. So temporall bleſſings doe not hurt the godly, as they doe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; becauſe they haue the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe veines of knowledge and pitty, ſo that the deadly fumes of that henbane, the loue of worldly things, neuer paſſe to the heart: If riches increaſe, if ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours increaſe, they ſet not their hearts vpon them. For as the Wiſe man ſaith,<note place="margin">Syr. 39</note> 
               <hi>Omnia bonis in bonum,</hi> All things to the good &amp; godly are turned to good. If then we will giue our own ſoules ſatisfaction, touching this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent duty of goodnes, which is <hi>Totum hominis,</hi> All that can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of a man: let vs not leane to this falſe deceiuable tree of the world, that is cut thorough, and deceiues and ruines all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephants and mighty men of the worlde, that leane vnto it: nor let vs ſo greedily ſwallowe this Mandrage which ſtupifies our vnderſtandings and reaſons,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:7797:82"/>congeales our deuotion, &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and caſts vs into a dead ſleepe of ſecurity. Nor let vs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture vpon this henbane, that ſo ſoone kils the heart, except we bee aſſured of our ſelues, that we are thoſe holy Sparrowes, that will not ſuffer the fumes of it: that is, the loue of the worlde to poſſeſſe our hearts. For it is this goodnes onely, that is like vnto <hi>Salomons</hi> ſiluer,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10</note> and anſwereth vnto all. I know the world doth like much better of <hi>Salomons</hi> ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, then of <hi>Salomons</hi> goodneſſe: but it is for want of that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with goodnes, that they haue with ſiluer. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, that in his time, <hi>Nihil erat tam po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulare quàm bonitas;</hi> There was nothing that the people of <hi>Rome</hi> affected more then goodnes; and what made goodnes ſo popular, but the practice of it, and the number of excellent perſons, as <hi>Cato, Fabritius,</hi> and many more, who loued and countenanced it? Such men are the very barres,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:7797:83" rendition="simple:additions"/>gates, and brazen walles of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. Therefore one ſayd wel,<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> that in a kingdome well gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the want of one good man was more, then the famine of bread and wine. For wee haue ſeene God ſend a famine for the demerits of one man, and after that, abundance for one good mans ſake. What goodnes hath a common-wealth, if it haue no good men? And what wants it, if it want not good men? To which purpoſe is that,<note place="margin">Clem. in Ituer. lib. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> that he heard Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeake it: That if <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> had not interceded, when God burnt <hi>Sodome</hi> and her three ſiſters with fire and brimſtone, the whole world had been burnt, ſo wicked was the whole worlde at that day: and yet at <hi>Abrahams</hi> prayer, the iudgement fell onely on <hi>Sodome</hi> and her three ſiſters. And ſurely it ſeemeth, that the prayer of <hi>Lot</hi> ſaued <hi>Zoar,</hi> albeit the Inhabitants were moſt flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and wicked men. And of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:7797:83"/>ſuch value are good men, that a Father confeſſeth,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> whenſoeuer he heard a knell ring for the dying, his ſoule was ſore perplexed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee ſhould pray for the good that die, that they might liue lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or the wicked that liue, that they might liue better. For that there is as great reaſon to weep for the life of the badde, as for the death of the good. All this that I haue ſayd, is to ſhew the vnua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable worth of goodnes &amp; good men, and what preſeruatiues they are to that State wherein they liue and are cheriſhed.</p>
            <p>Now muſt I then conclude all I haue to ſay, in theſe three ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations out of the Text.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, that vnder this one vocable of Goodnes, is compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the ſubſtance and marrow of piety, religion and honeſty; and vnder that word, Man, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man liuing of what condition ſoeuer: whereby we may be put in minde of an excellent grace, that ſhould be amongſt vs: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:7797:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnity. That wee ſhould bee all, <hi>Tanquam vir vnus,</hi> As one man in euery thing that tends to the glory and preſeruation of the Church and Policy; to bee thus one, is to bee all and more then all: to be more or leſſe then thus one, is in the end, to be none and leſſe then none.</p>
            <p>Diuiſion is an ill companion to glory, perpetuity and ſafety: A houſe diuided, a Kingdome, a City, cannot ſtand. Truth that cannot lie, hath ſpoken it, and thoſe diuided ſhall ſurely feele it. One is the beginning of all num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, without which no number can bee, into which all numbers are reſolued, and by addition of which,<note place="margin">Acts 17</note> numbers are multiplied. So God hath of one blood made all nations of men; nay, wee are all the of ſpring of God himſelf, who is <hi>ſimpliciſſima vnitas,</hi> The moſt ſimple vnity. And we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee of the number of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, except wee beginne, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and end in one; nay, reſolue
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:7797:84"/>all as one man; and ſo by addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this one, ſhall we be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed as the ſtarres of Heauen which cannot be numbred.</p>
            <p>All excellent things in nature are but one: one Frmament, one Sunne, one Sea, one Earth, one Fire, one Ayre, &amp; euery pretious ſtone, is but <hi>vnio,</hi> an vnion of many beauties and perfections in one body. All excellent things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue nature are but one: one God, one Faith, one Hope, one Charity; ſo in my Text, one man, one goodnes: therefore if wee will bee excellent any kinde of way, in nature, or in grace, wee muſt be one. As many members make but one body, many bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches but one tree, many graines but one loafe, ſo many perſons by faith and loue, make but one Church. My doue,<note place="margin">Cant. 6</note> my vndefiled is but one, ſaith Chriſt. Ye are all one in Ieſus Chriſt, ſaith <hi>Paule:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3</note> there is neither Iew nor Gentile, Engliſh not Scottiſh, bond nor free, male nor female; but all are
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:7797:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>one.<note place="margin">Gen. 45</note> What then? Then fall not out by the way, ſaith <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to his brethren:<note place="margin">Gal. 5</note> If you bite and deuour one another, take heed ye be not conſumed one of another.</p>
            <p>Charity and loue is like the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and mortar, that of many ſtones and thoſe different in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, makes one wall, able to keep off the violence of many ſtormes. Like the ſeed <hi>Piſtillij,</hi> that of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry peeces of fleſh in one pot, makes not onely good broth, but alſo one firme lump. For wherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the ſeeds of charity ſowne in the heart by the holy Ghoſt, do boyle, they work a ſound co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of natures in themſelues moſt diuided. Whereſoeuer is <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas,</hi> goodnes, there all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are but as one man: euery one labouring the good of another, as his own. The Poets feigne, that the three Gorgons being three moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſiſters, had all three but one eye, which they lent one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by turnes: ſo muſt wee lend not onely all the eye of the heart,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:7797:85"/>but euen all the good wee haue receiued to the good of others. For as there are many members of the body, yet but one heart to impart life to them all: ſo all cit wee are many, yet muſt we haue but one heart: the multitude of beleeuers haue but one heart,<note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> one ſoule. God will giue them one heart, and put a new ſpirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. Shall the wicked ſay,<note place="margin">Ezek. 11</note> 
               <hi>Marſupium ſit vnvm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 1</note> let vs haue all one purſe, and ſhall not wee much rather ſay, Let vs haue one heart? Beholde how good and ioyfull a thing it is, for brethren to dwell in vnity? Firſt, it is good. Secondly, pleaſant.<note place="margin">Sen.</note> 
               <hi>Et nullius bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſine ſocio, iucunda poſſeſſio,</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion, there is no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in any poſſeſſions. Thirdly, it is deare; for brethren: and what more deare then they? Fourthly, it is ſafe: for <hi>in vnum,</hi> they dwell in vnity. Many vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ſouldiers are not eaſily ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: many ſtickes in a bundle, many ſmall hayres in a lace are
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:7797:86" rendition="simple:additions"/>not eaſily broken, by the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt man.</p>
            <p>Conſider,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that this goodneſſe is the true ſtampe, figure, feature, and ſhape of a perfect man, and deliuers vs all the dimenſions of a good Chriſtian. Would you make choyce of ſeruants? Here is their full dimenſion, goodneſſe. If he haue it not, he is no fit ſeruant: for he is not man, but beaſt. Will you haue a wife choſen out of the multitude? Beholde here is her dimenſion too, euen goodneſſe. If ſhe want this, ſhe is no fit wife. Would you haue a magiſtrate to your liking? Here is his dimenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo, euen goodneſſe. Would you haue an excellent preacher? Here is his dimenſion, goodnes. If they want this, they are no fit magiſtrates, no fit preachers. And the ſame man we ſay: of all ſorts of men. O that God would giue vs the goodneſſe of his grace to chuſe our wiues, and ſeruants, our magiſtrates and preachers by this dimenſion. Then how happy
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:7797:86"/>ſhould maſters of Families be in their wiues and ſeruants? How bleſſed ſhould the Church bee in their magiſtrates and preachers?</p>
            <p>What miſchiefe the want of this direction works in all eſtates is well ſeene, and lamentably felt. But eſpecially if the ſeruants of kings and Princes be not aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for their goodneſſe. If the wife and ſeruant know not God, feare him not, leade not a godly and Chriſtian life, they are ill choſen wiues and ſeruants. If the magiſtrate and the preacher doe not the like, and make a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all their wayes; they are but ſtaynes to their places, and banes to their owne Soules. It is not wealth, nor wit, nor beauty and kindred in wiues: It is not ſharpeneſſe of witte, excellency of ſhape, Learning, wiſedome, nor other excellent qualities in ſeruants, that makes them fit, but onely goodneſſe. It is not witte, and experience and skill in the Lawes and policy, not eloquence
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:7797:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>and profoundneſſe in the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and preacher that makes them fitte: but onely goodneſſe. For that is the whole dimenſion of an excellent man, and what hee wants of that, hee wants of Man.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſeeing goodneſſe is ſuch, that it delights God, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, men, and all the creatures; and euery good giuing &amp; perfect gift, is from aboue: Let vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by all holy meanes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint our ſelues with this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſo we may procure the continuance of Gods goodneſſe to vs, and turne away his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from vs. You cannot but remember how that for want of this goodneſſe amongſt vs, God hath taken his goodneſſe from vs, and ſcourged this kingdome with many plagues: Fires conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming many townes, and much treaſure and riches: and after fires, waters drowning many townes, and much lands. And after waters, peſts and ſickneſſe
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:7797:87"/>waſting and wandring thorowe the veines of this land. And after all theſe, worſe then all theſe, a deadly vnrecouerable blow, which ſtriking at the roote, lopt away the nobleſt, higheſt, and chiefeſt branch, the right eye of this land, the glorious Sun-riſing of a happy ſucceeding age, the very ioy of our hearts took away,<note place="margin">Pr. Hen.</note> I ſay ſuddenly, and for our finnes, for our pride, whoredome and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther monſtrous impieties; for want of goodneſſe, I ſay it againe and againe, for want of goodnes. Let vs take heede that our ſinnes prouoke not God any more: For as the wife Roman ſaid well:<note place="margin">Sen.</note> 
               <hi>In illa die qua luſerant nauigia, abſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur:</hi> In the ſame day that the ſhippes ſeeme to dally and play with the Ocean, in the ſame day are they ſwallowed vp. So was it with vs then, and ſo now: wee were vnder ſayle, top and toppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gallant: but ſuddenly a ſtorme came, that not onely made vs ſtrike ſayle, but brake our maine
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:7797:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>maſt cloſe to the hatches. God grant it neuer bee ſo any more with vs. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> would not let <hi>Dauid</hi> goe out to battell, leſt they ſhould extinguiſh the light of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> How much more ought our care to be, that our vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and impieties put not out the light of <hi>England?</hi> For our ſins are more like to do it to vs, then <hi>Dauids</hi> battles to them. God in his greateſt mercy continue his goodneſſe to vs, that this bleſſed ſparke of our hope,<note place="margin">Pr. Char.</note> this glorious beame of our comforts, be neuer put out, bee neuer eclipſed: but that he may come to his graue in a full age,<note place="margin">Iob. 5</note> as a ſhock of corne commeth in, in his ſeaſon: that the ſtones of the fielde may be at league with him, and the beaſts of the field at peace with him; that there may be peace in his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle all the dayes of his life, and in his death, the peace of God, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7797:88"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7797:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes,</hi> dwelling in Foſter-lane, 1619.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7797:89"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
